學術階段。
既廣泛又長進。
法律專業證書，即係我哋平時所講嘅PCL啦。誒，實習律師嘅合約。
常委會咧喺二零一三年嘅十二月咧就已定咗咧委任獨立嘅顧問進行全面嘅檢討。
bring up the meeting for a while. We finished the voting. May may I invite Mr. Wang to continue his presentation?
故此咧，律政司咧一直咧係十分支持咧常委會嘅工作，包括今次進行嘅全面檢討嘅。
對於誒期望誒提升咧誒法律執業者嘅專業嘅資格同埋水平嘅，就以應付香港嘅法律界當前新嘅需要同埋挑戰。
建設性嘅討論，我哋希望各持份者咧，尤其是係兩個法律專業團體啦，同埋三所嘅法律學院作為主要嘅持份者咧，係能夠繼續保持開放嘅態度，積極噉樣考慮報告書嘅建議。
為咗表示對誒呢個深具意義嘅全面檢討嘅支持咧，律政司咧誒已經喺二零一五年嘅三月咧，向常會咧提供咗一筆過嘅一百五十萬港元嘅撥款作為資助。
啊！律政司一向咧係重視香港嘅法律教育同埋培訓方面嘅發展嘅，因為法律嘅教育咧以及法律專業咧唔單止咧係為社會服務，亦都對法治咧係更加有深遠嘅影響。噉啊，投身法律教育以及法律專業每一位咧都係法治嘅把關者。
誒對上嘅一次咧，就香港整體嘅法律教育同埋培訓制度咧，作出嘅全面檢討同埋相關嘅顧問研究報告咧，已經係喺二零零一年嘅八月發表㗎啦。噉啊，自此之後咧，情況出現咗多番嘅發展啦，而且法律專業咧亦都面對好多新嘅需求。
而全面檢討所涉嘅職權範圍咧，已經長列咗喺我哋較早前咧提供咗畀委員會嘅文件裏邊嘅第四段裏邊㗎啦。而最終報告書嘅內容所涵蓋嘅題目係非常之廣泛啦，包括香港嘅法律教育同埋培訓嘅現行架構啦，誒法律教育嘅。
多謝主席。
誒。
of the consultants.
在April this year。
response of the law society to the interim report.
And really, those would be the main points of the bar association in relation to the views of the consultants.
and there is a further report which is published in May, in answer specifically to the.
Of having the LSE, the Law Society Entrance Examination, we agree with the views of the consultant in total on that score.
And these three reports, actually, the bar association has read them in details. And in fact, there was a committee in charge of that, and the.
And for the reasons already given in the final report, which is further elaborated in the response to the law society's interim challenge.
Therefore, for this reason, actually, I don't think that we need to go through the details of the arguments of the consultant because they are all embodied in the report.
結論 of the bar association and the views of the bar association is already published in a paper dated the 21st of June, which has been submitted to this panel.
By and large, the bar association agree with the consultant's final assessment, and in particular, the bar association also agree with the conclusion that there is no necessity at the current stage to have a unified law school.
同埋實習大律師嘅培訓，同埋香港以外嘅資格認可考試等等。最終報告書所提出嘅三十八項嘅建議咧，亦都揭露咗咧喺遞交嘅文件嘅附件裏邊㗎啦。咁大家可以可以見到啦，就誒上個月中發表嘅最終報告書所涉及嘅內容咧。
關心法律教育同埋培訓呢個議題嘅持份者咧，就必定咧會花時間考慮報告書嘅結論同埋建議嘅。律政司亦都會繼續積極透過常會呢個平台咧，與其他嘅持份者就最終報告書同埋當中嘅建議咧進行具體同埋有。
在此咧，律政司力都重申，誒法律行業嘅本質咧係一門服務社會嘅專業，誒唔應該視為咧只係一門嘅生意。而事實上咧，提供法律意見同埋法律代表嘅服務咧，正正就係尋求公義同埋爭議解決嘅重要一環。法律界每
每一位咧都係守護誒法治嘅守門人嘅中堅分子，因此咧，我哋認為咧，就法律教育同埋培訓嘅任何改革咧，都必須係以公眾利益作為最終嘅依歸嘅。我哋亦都樂意咧誒繼續聆聽各委員以及各出席者嘅寶貴意見。多。
好多謝黃專員。咁而家咧就係我會請啊今日嚟嘅團體發言。咁首先咧，我會係請啊香港大律師公會嘅代表陳敬生資深大律師發言嘅。請陳資深大律師。Thank you, Chairman.
律師協會已經實際研究了三份報告，從顧問們，有相當細節。總共三份報告。第一份是暫時報告，發表於去年十月。第二份是最終報告，發表於。
In relation to the views of the law society, in particular, those were summarised in the consultant's last report published in May. Last May, we also agree with the consultants, in particular, to their views on the disability.
有個 role to play。
到PCL stage。
Obviously, we we feel that since.
and that is why we think that it is important that.
And for all these reasons, we feel that we should respect the view of the consultants in their conclusions.
and in relations to the view expressed by the law society, the bar association wants to add the word of caution.
certainly we agree that the law society should have a very important role to play on the mission of solicitors.
所有啲 stakeholders should work together to devise a system for the qualification of the two legal professions.
As a matter of record, of course, in the interim report, the consultants had once suggested tentatively that they should be moved.
That of course, that there is equally, likewise a high dropout rate for those whose initial intention is not really to join the bar.
但係， in so far as the overall conclusion of the consultants are concerned， 有兩個特別的區域，係巴爾唔完全同意結論。
但係，它係錯誤嚟嘅，假設律師事務所係獨家，係唯一嘅守門人，為平等同質素，為律師而設。
The PCLL is a common qualification. Certainly, stakeholders like the universities also have an important role to play on the standard of admission.
The first is in relation to the suggestion that civil and criminal procedures should remain as an undergraduate course and not moved to the PCLL.
And certainly, the bar association, whose qualification is also derived from the PCL, is certainly have a role to play. And in in fact, of course, the standard of the solicitors would also affect the work of the barristers. And that's why, indirectly, of course, the bar also.
plus the fact that of course that the in so far as experience tells us that in the bad years where the trainee contracts are not in adequate supply are not in adequate supply there is a rush of the people joining the bar and the consequence is.
That.
and therefore, say for instance to suggest.
The bar association was in total support of the.
The last thing I like to mention is the recommendation of the consultants on the.
and certainly because by definition, procedural law is quite different from jurisdiction to jurisdiction.
barristers in Hong Kong, in fact, a lot of barristers chambers are pretty small, with say for instance less than ten members.
因此，它就係一個比較好的方法。
The other thing that we don't quite agree with some of the suggestions of the consultants is in relation to certain of the proposals on pupilage.
We think that by and large, the consultants are very much attracted by what they conceive to be the system in England for the operation of barristers.
barristers in chambers barristers chambers in England obviously are quite well established and a number of them actually have members exceeding a hundred.
所以， on those scores， actually， we actually feel that the consultants had not taken into consideration sufficiently the local conditions.
pupil's training should be put under the charge of a particular member of the chambers and so on may not really be that really suitable for the Hong Kong set up.
and therefore, to really run chambers as a sort of corporation-style office,ly is not really the system that we had in Hong Kong.
因此，我們認為大學應該真正仔細思考，決定是否應該開始教授民刑訴訟。
recommendation to move the two subjects to the PCLL stage, particularly because the PCLL a lot of the applicants are from graduates of other jurisdictions.
And furthermore, to suggest, say for instance, that there should be a sort of central publication of vacancies in chambers, this sort of operation may not be really very suitable for Hong Kong.
Published.
嗯。
謝議員， now。
On behalf the law society, I have this statement to make.
Bars LQE Law Qualifying Examination。
at the moment, due to a less than transparent.
some might even say bias PCCL admission policy of the free university.
那，那係唔同的。
Now more than ever, the society would benefit if more members of the public have good understanding of our laws.
因此，大部實際上會認為我們應該堅持現有的系統，就LQE而言。
And they are not really looked upon as sort of fresh barristers as soon as they pass the examination and get qualified to practise in Hong Kong.
The Law Society has always maintained an open door policy to allow an equal opportunity for law graduates who may become good lawyers to be given the opportunity to join the legal profession.
因為The Bars LQE was basically really a test for the transfer of practising members, of members who had already had a lot of experience in other jurisdictions to practise in Hong Kong.
Well, most of the arguments, in fact, are already settled in the written submission that we put before this panel, and I think for this reason, I really don't think that I need to trouble the panel members any further. I'll be prepared to answer questions arising out of our views.
好多謝阿陳景生資深大律師。而家我哋想請香港律師會嘅前會長洪運信律師發言。係你好啊，主席。誒，我未發言之前咧，我想請問誒，因為我會代律師會有個好簡短嘅陳述，但係個陳述係英文嘅，咁所以。
一共同入試 exam。
要 establish the law society examination.
to be the brightest, and thus making them better lawyers.
The law society has a duty to rectify these injustices.
LSE， as an additional pathway to PCCL。
We are losing talents, which may be detrimental to our legal profession.
We have publicly announced in January 2016 our intention to set.
The university have not given full cooperation to implement the CCE.
We are considering exercising our powers under Rule 7, bracket A, bracket two, of the rules.
作為結果，經過幾年與利益相關者討論，但他們沒有展現開放合作的態度。
所以，為避免一個別，所以為避免一個別，一個額外的審查，要由PCL學生。
Without an independent unified examination, there is no fair opportunity for students to test and prove their abilities on equal footing.
We are exercising our statutory powers under Rule 7 of the Trainee Solicitor Rule Cap 159 to set up the Common Entry Exam, I'll call it CEE from now on.
和不夠充足的PCL職位，一些本地和大多數海外法律畢業生，會否則成為好律師，被剝奪了機會和合法的期望，加入法律界。
Some graduates from two of the three PCCL programmes are saying that they find it much harder to get the better jobs because there's a perception that only those who got admitted to the oldest law school are perceived.
律師行僱傭訓練律師，正向律師公會講述，畢業於三個不同PCL課程的學生，未能達成統一的高標準，最適合加入律師行的職業。
嗯誒，請問主席，你覺得我應該係繼續用翻中文啦，抑或要？我哋完全可以誒用曬英文。You can just誒 speak in English without your speaking in Cantonese. But okay, I I speak in English then for the sake of the record. In the full version, yeah. Thank you very much.
who have not been offered a place in a PCOL course.
And those who fail to get admitted are not.
是 to offer an additional opportunity law students.
rather， there are a number of students who have obtained a good law degree。
Can I just explain the thinking behind the introduction of the law society examination?
LSC會係一個額外的途徑，進入律師行的法律專業。
that they are worthy of a training contract, with the aim to qualify as good lawyers.
It is not to add a further examination for students who have been given a place on the PCOL.
要取一個考驗，那打開給他們的機會，成為合格的律師，服務社會。
所以，如果三PCL提供者真係相信，那些受訓到PCL會做好律師。
To pass LSE，students will have to achieve the same standard as expected of the PCL graduates.
It is not something added on top of the PCIL. In fact, it is independent from the current PCIL programmes.
Then by analogy, these LSE students would be unable to pass the LSE no matter how much they tried.
The purpose of our LSE is to allow those who were rejected by PCL an opportunity to prove themselves.
Brian Gilchrist, you will continue the views of the Law Society, please. Thank you, Madam Chairlady. Well, I wish I could use Cantonese. I think I better stick to English.
shall be the same.
There will be no lowering of standards.
主席，多謝主席。咁誒。
係對住個麥啊入。
The purpose of the LSE is to provide an equal opportunity.
It is difficult to understand why there is such opposition.
Whether it is through an entrance exam, such as the LSE.
就會 lead to them being able to enter the solicitors profession.
或The CEE，或，as currently the PCOL。
The test for competency to proceed to a training contract and qualification as a solicitor.
到所有 intending solicitors， to enter the profession， so long as they reach the requisite standard.
到律師會的 desire to allow for additional means for qualified law graduates to have the opportunity to take and pass an exam.
我感謝你 for your time。好嘅，謝謝，Mr. Gilchrist。啊，跟住落嚟咧就係香港大學學生會法律學會嘅主席任朗軒先生請。
There can be no justifiable reason why such a qualified student should be denied the opportunity of taking an exam that allows him or her the opportunity to progress to a training contract and to qualify as a solicitor and serve the community.
We are doing this for the betterment of the public. The Law Society invites all stakeholders to fully cooperate with us for the sake of the public and for the legal profession. Thank you, Madam Chair. Okay，啊，多謝洪雲信律師。啊，而家咧係咪啊？另外一位嘅代表係Mr。
我哋香港大學學生會法律學會咧，其實就睇完翻《香港法律教育及培訓全面檢討顧問最終報告書》入邊咧，我哋歡迎呢一份報告書提出嘅建議嘅。咁首先想提出嘅就係剛才頭先幾位都有提到嘅，就係誒去到講緊誒法律專業證書課程啦。咁其實我哋認為咧，如果係
暫換法律誒暫換統一執業試，其實有助係我哋去尋求更加多嘅協議啦，去揾唔同嘅示範者。我認為都亦需亦都需要包括學生啦，去了解翻其實喺而家誒唔單止係職場上面或者係法律專業上面，更加係可能學界嚟講，我哋係點樣去睇呢一個嘅誒執業試啦。咁而我。
School of City University，please。
and I should say the quality at legal education benefits a lot from the close cooperation we have from the professions.
課程改革嘅問題，咁之前律師會成日講過咧，喺二零二二年嘅時候咧就會去誒。
Obviously, at the moment, there's a lot of discussion about the law size proposals for a common entry exam or a law size examination.
感謝主席。City University歡迎諮詢報告作為討論如何提升香港法律教育的基礎。
as regards numbers, City University, we increased our numbers on the PCCL by 40 for the double cohort and have maintained those increased numbers.
It's political question as to whether there should be more places. At City U, we believe we could have a further modest increase in numbers if it was necessary.
Over the time, I've heard three arguments about this, relating to emission numbers, consistency between providers, and most recently, desire to control, have more control on the entry course so as to meet the needs of the profession.
我哋認為，其實執統一執業試入邊有三個最主要嘅問題，亦都係我哋學生可能會比較去留意嘅。第一點就係講緊其實統一執業試其實係一個壟斷嘅問題啦。咁亦都係正正就係報告書入邊都講咗出嚟㗎啦。咁統一執業試其實就係令到誒律師會啦，其實佢哋會成為一個誒代替。
咗，我哋一啲嘅大學嘅客誒院校啦，去成為管理呢一班誒嚟緊新進律師嘅一個嘅機構啦。咁亦都其實有機會係令到即係一班而家現職近律師嘅人，同埋想去投身律師界嘅人咧，其實會有一個明顯嘅衝突喺度。咁而呢個衝突，我相信係好難去解決嘅。咁而引進我哋講緊誒唔同源。
院校同埋律師會、大律師公會，佢哋三誒三方嚟講咧，咁先係能夠去保持嗰個嘅公正性啦，同埋我哋頭先講嘅一個即係防止有利益衝突嘅情況出現。所以我哋相信，如果去推行咧，繼續推行呢個嘅統一執業試，其實有機會係令到呢個擔憂情況出現啦。而第二點其實嚟講咧，就係講緊一個誒。
係行呢個統一執業試啦。咁其實而家嚟講已經有一屆嘅同學咧，一啲嘅誒雙學位課程嘅同學，其實可能已經會去面對呢個嘅執業試。即係若果佢推行嘅話，咁其實呢個情況嚟講，我覺得係誒唔樂觀，亦都係唔希望會發生嘅。反而我咧希望係喺誒同學喺讀讀一啲嘅法學課程之前咧，其實應該要了解。
咗佢未來想執業嘅時候嗰個考試嘅模式啦，同情況噉，再加上啦，其實統統一執業試亦都會影響到可能有機誒有希望去投身大律師行業嘅同學啦。咁其實亦都係對於同學喺誒適應嗰個嘅考試模式同埋要求上面嚟講係唔誒唔樂觀嘅。咁所以希望啊～
喺誒推行呢啲呢一統一執業試或者係其他雙類型嘅考試，例如頭先講嘅誒律師會考試等等，其實都需要有透明度同埋去諮詢啦，而唔係誒好快嘅推行。因為頭先都講到，而家八零一九年咧，可能已經會推行呢個嘅考試啦。咁而第三點嘅時候，亦都誒我哋本會亦都會去考慮。
一個問題就係其實法律執業誒法律執業者條例咧，係咪真係去賦權律師會係誒去制定一個考試咧？噉我相信喺呢三點嘅情況底下，再加上咧，其實誒而家目前嚟講誒法學專業證書課程，其實佢喺嗰個批評誒喺公眾批評上面咧，或者喺公眾嘅反響上面，其實都冇。
嗯。
未獲梅陰。
on consistency.
律師會自設行使佢哋專業團體嘅權力，我哋可以理解嘅，但係恕我不能苟同。
In fact, I think there's a greater danger if you introduce a second alternative exam. There'll be more risk of inconsistency between the output from the different programmes being provided.
至於律師會五月份突然將佢哋原先倡議嘅統一執業試，切換為另起爐灶嘅律師會考試，我哋係深感不解。
We believe there are sufficient mechanisms at moment to ensure consistency of standards, and haven't really seen any criticism voiced in our assessment panels or boards about the standards that prevailing.
The profession is involved in every facet of the PCL programmes. They review the syllabus, they attend lectures and tutorials, they review exam questions and answer scripts.
On the question of the relevancy of the PCCL to the needs of the profession, I must say we are always happy to hear views of the profession about how the course can be developed over time, and we would be keen to engage in those discussions.
And indeed, at all times, we've been open to discussions with law society about this and other stakeholders, and we would welcome continued dialogue to try to produce the best system for the students of Hong Kong.
包括學士學位同埋專業證書嘅優化建議，香港大學嘅法律學院將會與上次委員會裏面各持份者響達至共識嘅前提之下，為公眾利益同埋學生福祉竭力配合，精益求精。
律師會代表曾響呢一個委員會裏面提及，響法律專業證書必修科入邊加入由佢哋擬定嘅共同試題，適用於三間大學嘅專業證書考試，並且由佢哋批決呢一個模式。
顧問報告所建議嘅背道而馳、大相徑庭，令到學生無所適從，因為學生係唔會知道應該或者點樣選擇個別課程，同或者考試到底係大學入邊嘅法律專業證書啊，定抑或係律師會嘅考試咧？
太大嘅問題啦！咁相信如果冒冒然去做一個咁大規模嘅改革，亦都係冇一個好清晰嘅指引畀學生咧。我相信係唔合唔理想嘅。咁再誒，你嘅時間夠啦，唔好意思嚇，陣間仲可能有啲機會畀你補充嘅，好冇都清楚㗎啦，意見。OK，the next one is a Professor Howells, Dean of the Law.
Thank you, Professor Howells。跟住落嚟咧，就係香港大學法律專業學係嘅係主任周偉信先生。請多謝主席女士。誒，法律教育同埋培訓常設委員會顧問響四月份完成嘅檢討報告入邊，有關對於大學法律教育。
係啊。
yeah.
誒。
我想問下。
對於 barristers。
regarding a unified law school or unified PCL provision programme.
見習律師聘約嘅誒，作為一個誒考慮嘅原則，另有睇法。
regarding the common entrance examination, sorry, regarding the law society examination, we do agree that even if
律師會有冇明確嘅數目，即係期望三間法律學院每年一共要收幾多個PCLE嘅學生，同埋除咗學歷同學業成績之外？
從有關佢哋所建議嘅律師會考試嘅資訊入邊，律師會似乎對法律專業證書嘅學額同埋修生嘅準則，特別係一啲有機會獲得。
喺一個咁匆誒倉促嘅時間表入邊，佢哋都唔會有充分嘅時間考慮律師會嘅誒。算我坦白，對學生係嘅建誒呢個建議對學生係毫無益處。
It would be possibl，e it might be possible that the bar association may also establish an exam that would allow students who have who are unable to directly enter into PCL to do another examination to obtain a second chance.
The rejected students are given opportunity to enter the PCCL. This would only be for those that would try to be solicitors. But what about those for barristers? Those students may may only have a chance to enter the PCCL through the school itself with their own results. and
其後響去年嘅十一月，將佢哋草擬每科嘅試題涵蓋範圍同埋標準，邀請三所大學嘅法律學院畀意見，我哋照辦如儀。而據我所知，三間法律學院嘅院長都曾經聯署邀約律師會嘅代表跟進呢件事情，然而一直。
官密論佢哋嘅法定權力如何呢一點，響上次委員會嘅顧問報告書裏面已經重複提及。但係貫貫徹佢哋從統一執業市開始嘅做法，響未有充分論證、未有具體執行細節嘅情況之下，宣佈響二零一九年是在必行。同上次委員會。
我哋響我喺呢度咧，懇請律師會放下佢哋對權力嘅執着，響上設委員會顧問檢討報告嘅建議同埋框架之下，繼續為社會同埋同學共謀福祉。基於呢一個協商協力嘅大原則情況之下，我想透過呢個機會向律師會代表提出兩個問題。
甚至一啲全職嘅法律工作經驗之外，有冇其他嘅條件應該一並考慮？多謝好啊，多謝啊啊周生咁跟住落嚟咧，就係香港城市大學學生會法律學會聯會臨時行政委員會主席梁希順先。
如果他們在自己的結果中，他們可能沒有考慮到可能性，即係律師公會會有提供一個考試嚟進入PCCL，因為律師公會只規管律師。所以，如果我們要處理呢個問題，我們需要處理一個公平性問題，即係只係想入。
Thank you.
嗯。
and finally.
Chinese University of Hong Kong。
study if they were to enter the PCCL.
首先， of all， in relation to the form and content of the PCL.
And if this continues, there will be too much competition.
Faculty of Law, the Chinese University of Hong Kong, please. Thank you, thank you, Madam.
OK，啊多謝啊梁生，啊跟住落嚟咧就係啊Professor Stephen Hall。
by means of deduction， there would be two JD students entering into PCL per LB student。
They are they are expecting to admit 115 JD students compared to one Lb student. That
Chairman, and it's nice to see you again in person after so many years. The I have I'd like to divide my comments into three parts.
existing among LLB students and it would have a suffocating effect on those that try to enter the PCLL but are unable to do so because of too many competition faced by the sheer number of people studying.
我會先講到形式和內容，然後再講到考試。
It is submitted that there may be more confusion caused when the PCL courses are merged, as the admission standards again will have to be recalculated. Different law schools have provided different standards of education, and with different courses provided, as stated before, it may cause students to be confused in choosing what courses they should.
我會像要提交，大學可能接受太多J.D.學生。統計從中華大學香港分校顯示，他們有兩倍多的J.D.學生，相比L.B.學生。和以參考香港城市大學的錄取，
Our next.
of the report of the panel of experts. Thank you very much. Okay. Thank you, Professor Ho.
Turning our attention then to the question of the law society examination.
especially having regard to the far-reaching changes and the preparations that will need to be done in order to meet that deadline.
Speaker would be Mr Christopher Knight from Chinese University of Hong Kong Faculty of Law. Has he come?
qualified vocational training programmes, which they say will serve as a qualifying basis for sitting the law society exam.
我係，我
of the panel of experts, that if there if there is to be any system of common assessment adopted in the PCLL for for the PCLPCLL providers must be involved in paper setting and examination arrangements for that.
has remained and remains now open to all discussions regarding the form and content of the PCCL, and in particular, we are we would like to emphasise our support for recommendation at least the first half of the recommendation six point four in the recommendation.
Chinese University has always been open to the views of the Law Society of Hong Kong and to all other stakeholders in the matter of legal education. I note that the Law Society is represented on the academic board of the of the of the PCLL programme at the Chinese University of Hong Kong.
我哋想指出，我們不接受有個案例，為引入律師公會嘅建議，為一個共同入職考試。喺佢哋最近嘅建議中，特別係，佢哋冇任何指標，作為替代，用佢哋嘅語言。
或even that it will be based in Hong Kong, or based or provided by by entities that are based in Hong Kong. The prepared start date in their proposal, which is 2019 to 2020, seems to us to be extravagantly optimistic.
We believe that there should be a moratorium. In this respect, we fully support recommendation six one. We believe that there needs to be a moratorium on the implementation of the law society's proposals. And in this respect, we fully support recommendation six one of the.
不。
hello。
Yeah, go ahead.對對住個麥就聽。Thank you.
所以唔係幾多數字，但係幾多個位數？你有喺度諗？因為你話你想提供。
It's not how many students that we're going, we plan to take on. Our philosophy is that there could be 600 students taking the exam.
Yeah, I just want to get get the basic facts right. How many potential students are you going to take on with the LSE? This is a question obviously for the Law Society. How many students are you looking at?
In order for them to pass exam, they have to reach the same standard as PCL student. No, but you must have some idea. So, may I just finish? Because it could end up six student out of the six hundred can pass exam.
places for those who couldn't get into PCLL a chance to become a solicitor. I get that point, but what I'm also hearing from the universities is that they are too willing to increase the number of places for PCLL each year. Now I'm trying to understand.
係啊，畀四分鐘噉啊，儘量啦嚇。噉我都會畀大家儘量完成一下。咁如果唔係咧，我哋有機會係第二輪嘅今日。咁首先咧，就係我想請阿郭榮亨議員副主席開麥入嚟。
About 40 students or so a year qualified as legal executives. Year, but for those students, I mean, the Law Society representatives talk a lot about issues of equity and fairness at the post-PCIL stage. But I would say this is an issue of equity and fairness at the pre-PCIL stage, and hope we'd have member support for this recommendation.
I'm here, Madam Chairman. But actually, the statement was made by my colleague. Oh, okay, you are together. Then I would invite Mr. Danny Gittins, Associate Professor, Hong Kong U School of Professional and Continuing Education. Please. Thank you very much. Hong Kong U Space would like to take this opportunity to highlight a different issue in the.
報告，從那提到的其他委員會今天，那是建議四點五，關於擬議創立一個先進的法律執行資格，這將允許一些法律支援人員直接進入BCIL。我確信所有在法律領域工作的人，都清楚法律支援人員所扮演的關鍵角色，例如法務助理。
legal executives. I mean, in the case of those working in law firms as legal executives, they already have to follow very detailed requirements laid down by the Law Society of Hong Kong. We at Hong Kong Youth Space run courses following those. Their experience is recognised by the judiciary into practice directions, which allow legal executives certain rights of audience in the High Court and the District.
但係，有個基本嘅issue of unfairness here，因為目前如果佢哋決定想繼續入行，加入法律界，佢哋會被當作是學生，要重新開始學法律學位。好多人都成功咗，但係呢個係一個需要，正如報告中提到嘅。
香港是 fallen behind other common law jurisdictions such as United Kingdom and the US, where they've long had procedures for recognising the experience and training that legal support staff can build up over many years of work. I mean, I should point out that in the United Kingdom, you've even had legal secretaries. Now, some of them have gone on to become judges.
Nobody is suggesting anything quite as radical as that in Hong Kong, but the consultants do recommend in recommendation 4.5 that Hong Kong seek to catch up with other developments in other common law jurisdictions in this area, and that providers of legal executive training courses work with local law schools and the legal profession.
If the
Through the LSE.
如果那係足夠去， cater。
another chance，that's all I'm asking.
who cannot get into PCL for whatever reason.
The same number of students that you are planning to take on.
我會 like to give an opportunity to those.
Universities will increase their places for PCLL say by 200 places per year.
This is not the first year that they decided to tell us that they can increase the places. But my concern are.
consultation in this respect. So what are the numbers that you're talking about? Because as the representative of the legal profession, I have to understand.
When are they going to have a chance to at least attempt an exam that they, according to what we predict, most likely they will fail because of standard? But I, I, my my point is.
所以，我我Cannot see why there's so much opposition. So you're talking about, let me finish first. So so you're talking about people who have failed in the past to get into PCL and you want to give them a second chance. That I get. But so what are the numbers you're looking at?
ballpark。 no， does it does it， I don't quite understand。 no， but you're talking about potential pool。 let me finish。 you're talking about potential pool of people， who you want to give them a second chance， right？ that I get。 but you must have some estimation as to how many。
Then there is really no need. No, there is because if the universities are willing to accommodate that. Yes. Let let let me the whole answer. Yes, thank you. The university has been telling us that they will increase places for X number of years.
those who have failed to get in in the past. now we are talking about let's say this coming September, 200 more places, so the the incoming applicants can benefit from the increase. but what happened to those who cannot get in and who's now working as a paralegal for the past five years?
要發展一個更先進的法律執業資格，那可能允許直接進入PCOL。當然，我們作為香港U Space，作為香港最大的法律執業訓練課程提供者，會非常樂意與法律學院及法律界合作，試圖實行這個建議。我必須強調，沒有任何質疑。
Of trying to provide some sort of backdoor route into the legal profession, anything like that. Of course, whatever final form this takes, all stakeholders would be happy to satisfy that standards are upheld. Also, as the largest provider of legal executive courses, we can provide some perspective. The numbers are not huge. I mean, we ourselves probably have about
Okay，誒，thank you，誒，Mr. Gettings。誒，我哋而家咧就係我哋嗰啲團體已經係誒完成咗發言，我就想將時間交畀我哋委員噉啊，希望大家盡快按紐，依邊我計算時間嘅。暫時嚟講係有四位咁咧，就誒，我首先咧就每一位委員咧就係。
所以，什麼？
啊。
誒，唔該，主席。
啊，洪洪律師有冇回覆？係。Sorry，I came here hopefully I can get。
誒，我印象中咧，呢個題目喺上一次嘅司法事務委員會係有討論過。
我點樣説？ not permission， but an understanding from stakeholders that what we propose is still a good idea.
It's okay, it's okay. Actually, I'm speaking to both of both of you. I hope that later on the discussion would be better. 啊，第二位咧就係周浩鼎議員。
what is the impact this LSE will have on the profession as a whole? So all I'm asking is for some basic numbers and facts that you are you must have in your possession. Because if you're undertaking this huge project of setting up a LSE, you must have these basic facts in your possession.
I mean, without that, why should I spend all the time and the effort to give you all the datas whether it will succeed, how many student can pass the exam? I don't think at this stage that is the issue. But how do you not have those? Ah, Dennis. Okay, wait. Sorry, I already answered your question. Yeah, let me.
Pause you, I have to pause you. I do not want to stop people speaking in the middle, but I hope that all of you understand. The rule here is you have to wait for the chairman or chair lady to call for your name. You are not supposed to overlap each other's discussion. But I just try to.
Let you finish what you say, but our members, I hope our members also follow this rule, and just let our guests also know about the rule. So we wait. I will try to give a little bit more time, be generous to people who haven't finished, because I know this is a very debatable topic. My apology.
誒，我自己又咁睇嘅嗱，上一次我聽會嘅時候咧，好明顯啊，聽到有好多代表都提過，對於個統一執業試嘅安排咧，佢主要係擔心，特別係啲同學咧，可能就擔心，我都唔知點掌握將來嗰個考試嘅情況，即係佢對於呢一個嘅，即係自己將來，因為。
當然呢個係對佢哋最切身嘅，因為佢唔明白或者佢有憂慮，將來究竟點樣去嗰個考試嘅模式或者嗰個要求究竟係咩咧？呢個我相信真係啲同學係多番表示有呢方面嘅憂慮。咁如果你話誒喺未解決到呢個憂慮之前咧，即係唔好操之過急。
咁突然間㧬佢出嚟咧，我都覺得有道理嘅。即係我諗，可能你話齋，大家如果有太大意見，咁咪可能要有啲嘢要問清楚咯。即係唔好話太過操之過急咁去㧬一件事。啊，反而咧，我就想借呢個機會講講咧，我特別同意求先啊啊Danny Gittings教授講嗰段説。
係。
申請唔到嘅。
考到呢個學位去讀。
佢點解即係要等咧？
嗰個申請比例有幾多係？
攤啲時間，好，跟住落嚟咧就係鐘國斌議員。
法律畢業，或者甚至乎有啲係外國畢業翻嚟嘅。
誒申請到呢幾間大學嘅PCL學位，佢可以有第二個渠道，令到佢可以慳翻啲時間啦。
嗱，如果有一個用家，或唔係首先用家長嘅角度咧，即係你如果一個誒仔女去讀完。
如果即係律師會而家有一個誒課程咁先算啦，係經過律師會再去考，起碼佢多個選擇，兩條腿走路。噉你年青人，你今次啊未必。
咁如果申請唔到嗰啲，佢點咧？咁當然有啲咧就可能係讀誒兩年嘅part time啦。噉啊，有啲就可能再要等一年再考過。嗱呢啲我覺得咧，就真係有少少浪費年青人啲時間。
話誒特別提到咧，就係今次建議裡面嘅四點五咧，講到嗰個對於有啲法律行政人員咧，誒應該講就係話佢哋可能未必有一個學歷，但係咧佢哋有好足夠嘅誒事實上喺工作上嘅經驗，噉係咪應該要畀呢啲人設計一個機？
制畀佢哋啊，畀佢哋可以透過認可翻佢哋有啲嘅誒經驗，亦都可以畀佢哋有機會進入呢一個嘅執業律師嘅嗰個資格咧。噉我其實覺得呢個真係值得應該要諗嘅，因為畢竟有好多人咧，我相信咧啊，佢未必喺大學裡面攞到嗰個相。
相關嘅學歷，但係佢透過好多年嘅工作嘅經驗、實打實戰嘅經驗咧，佢其實可能咧嗰個嘅誒出嚟嗰個嘅啊啊水平啊，可能亦都係唔低嘅。噉我覺得應該畀呢啲人一個機會啦。咁另外一樣嘢咧，就係講翻嗱，頭先啊會長，我聽到。
嘅即係其實處理，如果佢嘅原意係希望畀翻一啲人係有一個second chance，即係畀翻人一個第二嘅機會啦。即係如果佢第一次唔得，噉佢起碼有第二啲機會再嚟過，佢可以有機會進入到嗰個誒律師嘅行業嗱。呢樣嘢咧，我自己咁睇，我都覺得咧人都應該係有呢一個安排畀佢嘅。
呢個我認同嘅，不過我只係想講咧，就係話嗱，大家如果個目標個諗法都係想去做到呢樣嘢，會唔會即係可能有啲細節嘅方式方法有所唔同，即係大家可以磨合到真係有咗個共識，咁去拱嗰樣嘢去行咧？我主要係呢個意見嘅啫嚇，唔該。你有冇人想問嘅？誒，我你表達意見，我表達意見啫。
主席，我相信我坐喺度咧，係差唔多唯一一個冇法律背景嘅人，都全部都係誒律師或者讀過法律背景，所以我咧用一個用家或者一個誒可能誒家長嘅角度睇呢件事，相對嚟講係比較中立。
而你係需要去再讀P.C.L.L.先可以作進一步作為一個執業律師嘅話，第一個問題我就係睇睇而家嗰個課程P.C.L.L.嗰幾間大學嘅學位嘅足夠程度，同埋有幾多係香港畢業之後或者外國翻嚟之後要。
咁所以變咗，我就覺得咧問題不大嘅。所以當然你話裏邊個課程誒或啲準則各方面咧，我覺得即係如果係律師公會又好，大律師公會又好，律師會或者大律師公會又好，大家如果坐低傾到一個大家認可嘅一個準則，大家都咁噉。
啊啊！
或者畀多個機會佢哋。
嘅誒誒基本入博資格。
根本係唔足夠嗰個學位。
好啊！時間夠啦，跟住咧係何君瑤議員。
咁然後咧，因為律師會嗰個誒。
係啦，即係我基本係睇你，總之一定有個法學嘅學位。
同埋，即係點解唔可以畀多個選擇啲年青人或者畢業生？
咁有啲考即係讀完嗰個你話誒second class honour嗰啲噉嘅，翻到嚟。
佢入唔到要等，又要等一年，或者讀part time要兩年時間，又係嘥多一年時間。點解唔畀多個選擇佢哋？
有份量嘅專業團體嘅話，我相信亦唔會差到去邊。所以我第一個問題就係。
所以，我認同你嗰個睇法，即係一個問題就係話，如果你本身幾間大學嘅PCL嘅學位係唔足夠嘅。
我唔記得中文係咩benchmark咧，噉我哋咧就話係一個誒二點二，即係second class誒second division。
哦，I'm supposed to be哦，OK，誒去答你嘅問題，即係我哋而家嘅構思咧，就係誒首先一定要有個LLB或者個JD嘅。
好啊，亦都係表達意見啫，係嘛？你想問邊位？問題咪個課程嗰個學位同埋即係申請嘅人數熱，係你會唔會係想問啊？律師會代表或者大律師會或者政府邊位可以回應啊？中議員嘅問題，係Mr. Hong，please，呀。
咁其實我哋嘅構思咧，我就希望係噉樣噉樣行。其實簡單啲嚟講咧，就係畀多啲人去試去考試，唔等於個考試會容易啲過㗎。咁最緊要係有機會去試啊嘛啊！噉啊，我希望喺呢個階段，我答到呢個問題。
社企。
個啲學生。
你都仍然係想爭取多一條。
專業團體佢對自己嘅新進會員入嚟有個。
佢要求喺二零二一年呢一個噉嘅統一考試，呢個若果以，
只要pass得到呢一個咧，亦都係係多咗一個渠道去入咗落去法律行業。呢個係咪我理解有冇錯啊？何師？
標準嘅期望呢個你你你你會反對喺邊度咧？我想明確多啲，多一個理由啊！係會唔會周生回應一下？係。
一條途徑令到誒有啲未必能夠讀到PCLL嘅同學可以去進身法律界，尤其是係。
我哋係要求三間誒誒法律學院咧有一個統一嘅考試，係LSC咧係畀嗰啲。
二零二一年嘅時候係純粹要求達至到律師會嘅嗰個入行嘅基準。咁呢個有冇即係佢而家已經講話二零二一啦？佢亦都會制定嘅個syllabus。咁喺噉嘅情況裏邊，作為
誒研究啊，較早前二零零一年開始啊，或者二零一三年嗰啲，我都瞭解到。但係我想知道update就最新嘅情況。而家我哋講緊嘅咧，律師會要求嘅係一個標準統一嘅考試，將會係二零二一年咧就會去生即係。
多謝主席。誒，剛才我就聽到咧，就誒清楚啦，明白。誒，首先我我申報啊，我亦都係喺二零一一年、一二年咧係律師會嘅會長，噉我亦都喺律師會嘅工作咧已經係超過咗廿二年。噉我我誒有部分嘅。
我哋嘅律師會下邊嘅solicitor branch啲solicitor profession，噉我睇呢一個咧就誒開多條途徑，絕對唔係有任何咩大嘅問題。咁呢一點我就想而家想問香港大學誒，就喺呢個問題方面講，以律師會嚟講咧。
呢一個咧，亦都紅印信前會長咧，剛才講唔係一定要係讀P.C.L.L，只要佢有J.D.或者L.L.B. first degree噉，然後就再考呢一個噉嘅L.S.C.啊，即係law society嘅嗰個嗰個college又好，或者叫C.E. Common Entrance Examination。
係，有少少誒，同我想講嘅係有分歧。唔好意思，首先咧唔緊要。其實咧個common，啊對唔住主席，我可以答下。可以答可以答。Common entry exam同埋LSC係兩回事嚟㗎。啊噉，首先咧CEE咧係讀緊PCL。
入唔到，收到，明白。讀PC嘅，多謝。嚇，咁嗰個考試嗰個程度咧，即係不能夠pass嗰程度咧，不下於現有PCALL嗰程度。呢個就係我哋想做嘅人。學軍容易入，多謝主席。啊，我我point即係話，我嘅理解，而家我。
多謝何議員。
於學生咧，最嚴重希望冇個friend人，因為我都讀過香港U，讀過City U嘅。
誒頭先誒律師會代表咧，其實都提過多一個途徑。
而據我理解咧，三間大學可以提供嘅PCCL課程嘅學位，大約係去到七百五十左右。
好，多謝。誒，跟住咧就係我哋排第二輪，如果想跟進嚇，我儘量畀少少時間你哋跟進你嘅問題。誒，跟住係謝偉俊議員。
啊！我想提供一啲數字先啦。據我嘅誒預測咧，今年新誒報讀誒三間大誒三間大學PCL課程嘅申請者大約總數咧係一千二百位。
咧，如果係一千二百個全部都可以讀誒法律專業課程，又假設合格率係達到相當嘅程度，噉樣其實整個業界又係咪能夠有足夠嘅律師嘅聘約去容納到咁多嘅畢業生咧？
係，如果你要補充，可以講多幾句。好，咁另外我所知道咧，誒城市理工大學佢哋本身佢哋嘅PCL入邊咧，都有一個面試嘅機制，係特別畀一啲第一次申請報讀失敗，而有第二次再申請嘅同學咧，係一個第二嘅機會嘅。
去有誒第二次嘅機會。其實咧，據我所知，第一香港大學本身喺我哋收生嘅時候咧，我哋都有提供面試嘅機會畀一啲咧，可能喺學業成績上面誒掹掹緊或者係勉強一啲嘅，能夠係去誒都通過面試咧，係有機會進入去入讀PCL嘅。
咁其實頭先律師會都講誒嗰個佢哋所新誒誒推動嘅呢一個誒律師會嘅考試咧，其實唔一定代表佢哋可以考到。咁其實容許我反問一句咧，就係到底而家響律師嘅專業入邊，每一年大約係有幾多份見習律師嘅聘約咧？
多謝主席。誒，我啲問題就係個樽頸位擺邊咁解啫，即係喺PCL嗰度啊，定還是留翻喺嗰個啱剛才講嘅討論咧，喺個合約個階段咧，定還是eventually喺嗰個做律師個階段咧，或者大律師嘅階段咧？咁噉，似乎剛才聽到阿洪運信先生咧就誒講佢。
佢哋一來係比較冇耐性咧，因為已經咁多年咧，大學都話要加n咁咁多x咁多年都話要加位加唔到噉。咁呢個係誒資源上問題上啦，大學本身有其他困難咧，我哋再討論咧。但係我原則上，我即係我我我我剛才何君何君耀員申報咗啦，我都要申報下啦。我亦記做個大律師，做個律師讀個P。
時候亦都，如果冇一千個咧，都起碼八百個員工喺我手上咧，係處理過關於特別我最喜歡咧，就係畀機會畀嗰啲係誒mature students或者係想唔係學法律出身，但係中期想轉行做律師嗰啲誒同誒人士，更或咧希望冇我friend到任何在座嘅人，但係我曾經有早期階。
應該冇。
係，洪律師。
諮詢過我哋嘅中心法院首席大法官。
咁先仲喺度問翻私分空咧，我覺得有少怪。即係講你咪代表我哋業界嘅咧。
係，誒，因為阿阿謝議員，你嘅時間用曬，你會係想有回應咧？我我我再排隊啦，嚇。好啊，好。咁跟住咧就係阿楊嶽橋議員。
頭先我答出嚟冇，咁但係咧，我個睇法即係好似頭先之前我講，如果我哋業界係有個共識，覺得呢個唔係對社會真係有啲咩好大影響嘅提議嘅。
我想了解一下今次律師會呢一個咁有創意嘅誒呢個LSC嘅改動。請問有冇諮詢過我哋嘅中審法院首席大法官？
洪前會長，誒律師咧，大家都係即係事務律師咧，係誒需要咧係喺執業嘅時候咧向法庭宣誓嘅，咁都係要向法庭咧係負責任啦。
主席，我冇乜嘢好申報嘅，我一個普通嘅大律師仔，噉啊，當然冇其他即係同事噉樣又嚇，又讀過唔同嘅學校，我讀過Hong Kong U P C L L就係咁多。我想請教阿洪律師。
段咧係誒好多同有好多學生，好多年輕人同我投訴咧，係C.D.U嘅畢業生咧，C.D.U嘅P.C.O學生咧係揾唔到工嘅。Hong Kong U都係著數嘅。不過當時我最中意請C.D.U嗰啲學生嘅，因為嗰啲覺得佢哋咧係有時underdog咧，佢哋個感覺咧個鬥志咧仲強嘅。反為P.C.O咧嗰啲好多係根本誒對面仲好多Hong Kong。
香港於學生，佢都係根本係認為讀香港於個law係威水嘅。本身唔係有咁有commitment或者conviction去做律師嘅，但係都係so happen個system即係好似香腸噉。組出嚟之後咧，佢哋跟住喺度製到落去，所以佢哋個對於法律嗰個嗰個誒承擔咧、抱負咧，往往係唔夠嗰啲咧係啊。
誒受迫害過或者係誒甚至之前咧誒，如果我用翻一個例子舉舉例咧，SEN students啊，嗰啲學生有special need嗰啲student咧，法律界一樣有好多人係咧，佢係special need，因為佢哋以前讀書嗰陣時，佢哋發奮嘅機會咧，發奮讀書嘅時間咧係遲啊，佢哋唔係嗰啲乖乖仔乖乖女咧。
聽住父母話咧，就讀讀咗法律學位出嚟就先做律師。往往係嗰啲做一輪嘢之後捱嗰輪之後咧，再翻翻讀翻，認為覺得自己真係中意法律嗰啲咧，係更加以後個成績更加好嘅。所以我完全咧，我我有啲尷尬講呢個講説法，因為咧我不嬲同律師會有啲尷尬位嘅。但係我覺得呢一次咧，我完全支持。
師會呢個做法，因為咧呢個係一個比較choiceable choice嘅，即係我覺得係畀機會畀我哋社會上任何係誒冇係循住我哋認為應該行嘅軌道誒過錯過咗個時間，甚至咧係比較年年長之後先發奮先揾揾到自己興趣抱負嘅人咧，多個機會去做噉。
由呢一點咧，當然我明白到，亦都同意剛才有，無論係Professor Gittings就好，或者係侯君源有誒講關於話贊成，對唔住，係咪？係啊，應該喊誒，好ever。關於嗰個誒執業嘅執咗業嘅行行裏邊嘅並非律師嘅人士咧，可以係從誒其他機會進入呢個行業，但係。
嗰個講法都係只係一半之誒，係解決咗問題，因為佢哋只係畀個有機會考P.C.L.O.，而唔係畀佢直接咧可以經過呢個L.S.C.之後咧，直接有個training contract嘅機會。咁所以呢個我覺得可以再諗多少少，因為事實上我經驗咧誒，包括我哋嘅前任律政司司長啦，都係曾經係經過呢啲途。
暫時未有。
咁點解？
最高嘅負責人。
對住我哋司法機構嘅。
你會唔會係將呢一個？
咁請問啊，洪會長幾時會有呢個定案咧？
有啲乜嘢嘅啊，即係幫到我咯～
係，洪律師。我都唔知道嘅答案。係，好。主席。
洪會長諗住幾時係諮詢馬道立法官？係，誒，洪生，我有定案，我通知你。
又要企起身嚟反對嘅，噉我同司長講喺呢個階段，我唔覺得會。
我想了解下，咁洪會長今日係代表律師會嚟，係向大家介紹推介呢個L S C嘅好處。
洪會長，究竟喺你哋決定要落實呢個LSC嘅過程裏邊，你哋嘅嗰個事實基礎或者你哋即係嗰個finding？
構建呢個決定嘅呢啲事實理據，都會呈第一份畀司法機構參與咧。因為我哋好想有，我哋就得唔到啦。咁唔知司法機構會唔會有呢個榮幸能夠睇到咧？
途徑咧，當年當然係可能競爭冇咁大啦，但係起碼都有機會咧，可以係喺一個比較年長嘅時候咧，先至係再qualify即係一個suitor。我覺得我覺得即係呢個方向咧，誒似乎聽阿洪先生講咧，佢哋並非嚟立法會攞我哋嘅bless攞我哋嘅approval。佢只不過如果blessing嘅話咧，就誒更加好咁解啫。噉我亦都當然咧。
誒，我剛才聽到話，啊，郭家誒郭榮亨議員咧，同阿洪先生嘅嘅對話咧。咁當然我哋嘅rule本來已經守規矩嘅，不過大家都知道咧，立法會就已經唔係一個好嘅示範嚟㗎啦，所以搭聲經常發生嘅事㗎啦。不過我覺得，如果誒郭榮亨問嗰啲問題咧，倒不如作為大陸界代表，你應該一早知道好多問題嘅。點解你而家好似乜都唔知咁？
主席，我想請洪律師。我相信洪律師，你一夫當關咁有堅毅嘅諗法，要為法律界開創咁多新嘅職位同埋機會。我想了解一下，係律師會喺你嘅領導或者喺你嘅協助底下，具體嚟講有定係冇？
哦，噉我多啲嘅支持嘅情況底下，再同CJ去談論呢件嘢，咁有可能我覺得可行，CJ啊，定喺度低都唔覺得可行嘅，噉我唔知啊。但係我覺得喺呢個階段，如果我哋自己閂埋門都唔能夠有個誒共識嘅，即係如果某啲持份者。
其實我最初係一個好簡單嘅問題，冇任何前設嘅，想了解下，即係律師會平時一貫都同我哋司法機構，特別係首席大法官有咁多嘅聯繫嘅時候，點解唔順即係唔簡單向法庭或者特別係馬道立法官瞭解一下佢嘅提？
睇法，即係我想了解一下律師會特別可能係洪會長嘅心路歷程呢？主席係，誒，咁頭先佢已經好清楚答咗你，噉你會唔會有其他嘅？噉啊，洪會長會唔會喺未來短時間內諮詢一下馬道立法官咧？係洪會長，我一定會，始終都有一天一定要諮詢。噉。
長唔長進係我哋睇法唔同㗎喎。
我一定會交代，但係我唔可以話畀你聽幾時。
洪洪會長，誒，我一定會同誒。
我唔係好明點解洪會長剛才會係冇答案嘅咧，主席。
我只係好簡單想了解，律師會唔會有呢個決定，或者呢個準備，係去向司法機構交代？
啊，馬道立大法官講嘅啊，不過我唔知幾時啫嘛。你願唔願意undertake你係會向馬道立首席大法官交代詳盡嘅理據咧？
係，我諗誒，阿洪律師亦都已經係清楚答咗你嘅問題㗎啦。其實啊，咁跟住就我自己嘅時間啦。咁跟我咧就首先要申報啦。當然我係喺香港城市大學啊，教書亦都睇住城市大學嘅PCL成立嘅嚇，一九九一年。噉我又喺Hong Kong U喺香港大學。
讀P.C.L.L嘅自己本身咧，亦都係大律師公會嘅成員之一，咁所以真係好多重嘅身份。噉啊，就住誒我哋嘅常委會做呢一個師誒法律教育嘅誒報告咧，我都喺呢個委員會應該跟進咗有四五年嘅時間，咁亦都係。
誒真係意識到咧，就係誒呢個係誒同阿黃專員講誒，除咗我哋自己法學院同埋兩個律師會之外咧，確實咧，我哋係亦都係關注到呢個係要從一個社會嘅公共利益嘅立場去睇翻咧，而家我哋法律教育點樣係誒培養幾多嘅人？
才點樣培養咧？咁噉，其實我好高興今日除咗見到現任嘅同事啦，我哋法學院院長亦都見翻以前嘅同事，尤其是當阿梁同學咧，佢提到咧就係話，究竟而家嗰啲嘅J.D.嘅同學同L.L.B.嘅同學嗰個比例嘅問題嘅時候咧，其實我就想都畀。
畀大家咧係可以表達翻清楚啲意見，尤其是啲同學，啲今日嘅同學多數係LLB嘅，噉我亦都係有教LLB，有教JD，但係我冇教PCLL嚇，咁所以咧我係比較中立啊去睇PCLL嘅問題。誒，究竟誒當年咧，其實我都想請，譬如啊，我我記得啊誒有一啲。
嘅誒教授呢度咧有參與當年嘅辯論嘅，其中一個就係話咧，其實讀J.D.同埋L.L.B.就唔一定要做律師嘅噉樣。噉我睇下有冇教授想誒都參與去講下佢哋點樣睇，即係今日有咁多嘅J.D.嘅學生啦，喺各大法學院。
誒第二咧就係誒嗰個市場嘅問題，的確啊，周生咧佢就提到究竟即係嗱，我就同翻去我都同唔同同事去了解過嘅，因為由於我哋立法會積極跟進之後咧，我亦都係誒客觀講咧誒各大學喺PCLL嗰度的確收多咗學生。
亦都有啲咧係誒做咗真係四五年，我好似睇到咧就八年啊，等八年先至入到而家嘅PCL，但係佢終於等到嘅後尾，終於咧都做到誒律師嘅嚇。我見到呢啲噉嘅同學咁而家係多咗嘅係誒誒嗰個比例同埋數目咧，特別包括。
詳盡嘅理據咧。
law schools. The latest figures that we have.
究竟嗰個市場能唔能夠消化曬，即係咁多嘅誒？
定案話你係咪可以無限期考到你八十歲？不過喺呢個階段，我可以話唔係考一次。好，阿周生咧。
喺海外嗰啲法學院畢業，有啲甚至係攞到咗second up嘅，即係二級嗰個second upper嘅嘅嘅嘅嗰個誒學位嘅誒。有啲因為以前咧好多係入唔到PCLL，而家就收多咗少少嚇，從嗰啲香港喺外國翻嚟嘅同學。噉我好想呢一度咧都。
都係誒，畀誒與會者都講一講啦。誒，因為咧誒，阿洪律師頭先佢特別提一點嗱，呢點咧，我覺得係大家係關心嘅，就係嗰啲咧有好多係等咗三年啊、四年啊噉樣咁嗱。佢如果譬如好似假設佢而你哋將來開一個新嘅途徑。
呢啲好有心嘅八年喺律師樓讀，又做咗讀咗LLB，就收你哋個個個考試。咁如果佢考你哋嗰個考唔到，佢又能唔能夠再排翻呢個誒PCLL？即係即係究竟嗰個關係將來會係點咧？同埋咧，的確我哋都係想大家表達下。
同學佢加入去法律呢個行業咧噉樣，噉啊時間都有限嘅。不過誒，儘量譬如阿洪律師啦，或者Professor Hall啦，Mr. Chow啦，都講講好冇嚇。譬如Mr. Chow，阿洪律師講先啦。即係我我霸住講先啦。好，律師會嘅態度咧就呢個試唔係考一次㗎，LSC。即係雖然我哋未有。
香港大學嘅香港大學嘅J.D.咧就比較收少人嘅，所以喺呢方面咧，我我諗我唔發表意見。但係我同意嘅，即係誒法律畢業生唔一定係需要做律師嘅。咁誒，至於海外翻嚟嘅誒有二級榮譽甲等嘅學生誒，的而且確，我哋都。
都唔係單單睇佢紙上嘅成績，我哋會比較審慎啲去睇，因為從我自己過去收生嘅經驗，我哋係發現有一啲紙上係二級甲等，但係咧可能喺個整體嘅分數同埋表現上面咧，未必係會合乎標準，又或者有時係因為有其他嘅因素，例如民。
文件唔齊備，又或者咧係喺某啲嘅關卡上面咧係誒失手，所以係第一次未必能夠入學。Okay, Professor Professor Hall, you want to participate the the JD and LLB from the the student? Whether we also supply or something? Yeah.
Professor Hall, Professor Stephen Hall, not Howard. Yeah, he hasn't participated. I remember Professor Hall. We had discussions on this before. Yes, thank you, thank you, Madam Chairman. The Chinese university has been pointed out to take the largest number of JD students of the three.
indicate that somewhat more than half of our JD students go on to apply for admission into the PCLL program. We take somewhere between two hundred and two hundred and twenty JD students a year. Last year we had fewer than one hundred and twenty of those students graduating out of the JD program applying to.
主席。
你應該畀個機會佢。
所有大學畢業。
what are the， you know further increase that you can promise now？
applications for PCR per year, ballpark, and that you are offering.
三十或 so， further places。 好嘅，啊，跟住落嚟係中國賓議員。
OK，即係增加咗。Yes，and then，呃，Civil U，and then Chinese U。
We took the same approach. We increased, I understand, by 40 in the double cohort and kept those numbers going forward.
所有即係有機會嘅人才，而唔係你去幫佢嗰個市場去篩選咗，即係都冇人請你。
咗唔畀機會嗰啲學生去讀呢啲課程嘅，所以呢個概念，我覺得係絕對係錯嘅。應該係培育。
佢自己裝備好自己，佢出去嗰個市場度，佢自己去拼搏佢嘅事。你唔可以因為噉樣哇，你哋未必請得曬啊啲人，所以咧就由大學篩選。
The size of the PCCL by how many? That is, that's a matter that's ultimately for the university to decide. But we are we are hoping for something in the order of of around about, I think.
過去喺過去嘅兩年，因為有誒兩兩兩批同時間嘅畢業生嘅時時候，我哋係即而且確增加咗學位。而我哋喺嚟緊呢年，雖然冇咗呢度兩批同時畢業嘅法律學院嘅同學，但係我哋會維持誒個學額嘅。
join the PCCL program with a fairly good success rate, but certainly not anything like one hundred success rate getting into the PCCL program. So those figures indicate that there are very substantial numbers of JD students who are not whose sights are not fixed necessarily on entering the legal.
profession, but who are aiming to use their JD degree to very often, especially in the case of our part-time students, to advance their careers in other fields of endeavour. So, so I think to suggest that the JD programmes in some way crowding out LLB applicants, I think is a misplaced. Okay. Okay.因為時間亦都夠。誒，我哋而家已經進行。
第二輪，第二輪咧，我哋係兩分鐘啦，好冇啊！第一位係阿郭榮亨議員。
rest of the legal profession. These are basic building blocks. You're talking about a major reform. How can you not have this information with you? Now, Chairman, I have a list of questions which I hope you would pass to the Law Society for written answers after this meeting. But there has been an accusation that the
Universities have been failing to increase places of PCCL over the years. Now, I just want to know whether that is factually correct. Can I just give you know maybe 20 seconds for each law school to answer this question, starting with Mr. Chow, perhaps? Whether you have increased PCCL places in the past years and
So increased by Hong Kong U and City U Chinese U. We Chinese U has increased its numbers. We started off with one hundred and fifty when we started our PCL programme. The last time we made a round of offers, we made one hundred and seventy offers, of which one hundred and sixty three places. So basically, my understanding is there are about one two hundred.
Over seven hundred. And in addition to that, Chinese University has placed a proposal before the university authorities to further increase the size of the PCCL programme. Sorry, can you repeat? I didn't. Sorry, I didn't speak into the microphone. Yeah. The law faculty has put a proposal to the university level authorities to further increase.
我我唔係幾認同，正話阿周偉信先生講咧，就話：喂，我培就算我培訓咗一千二百個誒一P.C.L讀完嘅學生出嚟，你個市場消化得到咩？你請得曬咩？你咁多你有咁多工作咩？啲呢個呢個係唔應該係一個即係教育人員去講嘅説話。
先叫我先。
好。
我我我搞咁多。
學鬼喺度畀人做咩啊？唔應該係噉。
嘅，咁呢個我就想澄清，若果以教學方面嚟講，大學嘅角度。
我所關注嘅係乜嘢咧？其實我所關注嘅都係學生將來嘅出路。
應該係咩情況之下都畀機會啲學生去有機會，佢只要裝備咗之後。
係嘛？唔好意思，誒副主席，我改著投票又好。好啊，你想邊個答你個問題啊？誒，Mr. Chow，啊，周生。
我聽得好清楚，律師會就講兩樣嘢，一就係第一，我哋要有個誒嗰個標準嘅統一。
學生讀咗你嘅PCL，你做得好好啦，已經好好嚴謹啦。若果係話律師會話要考多要pass多一個subject或者一個一個test嘅，咁個律師會絕絕對有權。噉你嘅反對係邊度？我就想聽清楚呢一點嘅。
你阿周生，你可以答問題。誒，多謝問題。誒，我諗而家律師會嘅建議係誒另闢蹊徑，唔係響考完PCLL之後再多一個考試。咁誒，我諗呢個誒，我哋需要搞清楚先。咁至於到底誒？
佢自己出去拼搏咯，呢個先係而家教育學，即係教育者應該要處理嘅嘅嘅態度咧。呢個我只不過一個意見，我唔會有其他問題。多謝主席。OK，啊，跟住係阿何君瑤議員第二輪。誒，多謝主席。實際上我都想跟進咧，即係剛才阿周生佢嗰度。
未講曬嘅，噉佢好似為咗律師會或者行業嗰嗰度擔心咧，就究竟係咪即係有噉嘅誒嗰個容量可以消化得到？咁但係誒，我覺得反而即係呢個係由律師會自己去考慮多於多於係誒係學院學術方面去諗。
嗰個質素個stander標準好重要嘅。我亦都唔係聽得到佢話誒。而家打開道門要有誒，總之逢人嚟咧，我就歡迎。唔係一個噉嘅flood gate open gate，唔係佢嘅policy呢個第一點。第二，佢只不過話律師會自己提出呢一個噉嘅誒LFC呢。
呢個新嘅途徑咧，係一個新嘅一個一個誒選擇。除咗三間大學嘅BCL之外咧，律師會係自己誒另闢新係。但係呢一個我亦都知道咧，係根據而家嘅誒LegalPractitionerOrdinanceCap一五九咧，律師會係可以。
把最後的關，佢係有噉嘅法定嘅權力去做。唯獨是我就希望，即係聽到大學方面嚟講，同專業團體要點樣作一個協調。而家究竟係咪我哋讀完三個P.C.L嘅任何一個三間大學嘅P.C.L係咪一定要pass呢個unifying examination？似乎嘅答案就已經係yes。
我希望可以。
咩令到你哋咁即係急切性要處理呢個問題？
第二個問題點解咁急？嗱，其實咧。
提出嚟個C.E同埋O.S.C，我希望大家明白係兩樣嘢嚟㗎，係唔同嘅嘢嚟㗎。
多謝，嗯，韓律師，唔該曬主席。誒，其實答第一個問題咧，誒，我嘅理解。
講真誒，我只係希望定出一個日子咧，等大家睇到律師會咧，就翻而家我哋。
咁其實我一定會聽，但係簡單啲嚟講，我我我嘅理解，我嘅理解，我係唔需要誒誒chiefship嘅批准。
喺我喺度嘅有朝一日可以見到成事啊！即係因為如果唔係咧，就成日喺度講。其實司長已經講十幾年㗎啦，但係冇辦法付諸實行。
我哋如果行使呢個權咧，我哋係唔需要誒誒首席大法官嘅批准，但係我覺得始終一定as a matter of courtesy，即係。
誒，如果覺得我係因為之前篩選等佢哋冇誒冇得入行嘅話，咁呢個並非我嘅原意。我所我就剛才發言嘅時候所提問，到底律師行業裡面有幾多嘅建築律師合約？只不過係關心學生嘅福祉。
啊，下一位社衞信議員第二輪。係主席，我哋誒對唔住啊，我我哋嘅嘉賓可能覺得我哋做咩隔嗰陣跳來跳去咩？我哋而家唔夠人咧，所以我哋隔離房投票咧誒比較緊張。噉我用爭取時間講講咧，即係我希望唔好話誒，即係話find到啊，我哋嘅副主席咧，我因為我奇怪就係我我做功能，雖然我而
而家係直選嘅議員，但係我做功能組別咧，功能組別嘅議員咧，理論上咧對你嘅行業裏邊嘅，特別你嘅米飯班主呢個係即係好熟悉佢嘅情況，實話咧應該係預先應該知道佢立場，佢哋點樣諗法，實話幫佢哋去誒再defend佢哋position噉。我今日比較奇怪啲，唔好介意我問呢個問題，究竟即係點解會搞成噉樣咧？噉我誒當然。
我亦都理解到誒師會佢哋嘅睇法，亦都剛才問過有阿梁喬賢問咧，就差唔多盤問方式咁問阿阿洪雲信先生咧，就究竟你有冇同個CJ有傾過咁？噉我亦都有奇怪，因為誒究竟係點樣咧？我都有少少誒打咗突，因為我以為應該呢啲都係會大家嘅溝通。雖然咧，就算好似基本法第三七十三條七。
即係話誒，終審法院嘅委任法官都要經過律師，經過法經過立法會去即係同意咧。都即係我哋問嘢問題都唔啱嘅，即係都要即係我哋橡皮圖章過就算嘅。咁同樣道理咧，我相信律師會做呢啲嘢咧，C.J.都可能會係橡皮圖章式嘅啫，即係係一個禮貌式嘅禮節式嘅要要求法律上或者我請，如果更正我，如果我講。
講錯嘅話，或者韓雲順先生有冇乜嘢法律上嘅嘅要求咧？係你哋任何嘅改革呢一方面係需要CJ嘅一個正式嘅通過先可以執行咧，有定冇咧？如果係點樣咧？第二咧，我想請問問就請問陳太敏問你哋今次呢個誒改革咧，雖然我係原則上贊成，不過timing上咧比較急嘅，有冇啲？
噉。
我而家係用中文發言啦。
嘅影響，即係如果唔係咧，可能你哋嘅意見係唔會咁大，即係都想聽下究竟你會覺得點解會有咁大嘅一個影響？
變做係一個vocational training嘅時間，即係P.C.嘅時間咧，做個樽頸啊！亦話係要等啊，所有學生已經係進行曬所有嘅。
咁所以你話個日子係唔係？喂，阿阿Stephen，你一定要喺嗰日做到咧。其實我可以答你唔係嘅。我亦都明白啊誒，logistic嚟有可能真係未必嗰個日子做到，但係。
你就一齊，或者阿陳敬生大律師都係可以講嘅，同埋政府咧就順便都誒有補充嘅咧，就喺誒我呢個都補充埋啦，好唔好啊？咁咧就誒首先或者呢邊熱烈啲嘅，我請阿陳敬生資深大律師講先，補充先。
其實一個幾理想嘅，但係有一樣嘢要記住就係，就算大，就算加咗PC啊，加咗若干嘅位，多多二三成嘅位咧，呢個比例咧，我相信都唔會有改變嘅，因為咧多餘揾唔到拼藥嗰啲就去曬做大藥師。
客即係有禮貌地啊！我一定會問翻誒誒馬大法官佢嘅意見。咁誒，如果佢就翻某啲嘅誒，即係我提出嘅嘢，佢覺得有保留或者誒誒某方面佢覺得可以做多啲。
所以我而家定出嚟係not earlier訂嗰啲日子嘅噉，但係我希望咧係一個合理嘅時間裏邊咧可以執行到咯。好啊，我咧就誒會喺我嘅發言之後咧就索性係請係啦兩邊咧都作補充同埋即係最後嘅補充同埋總結，所以我咧就講少少啊。
第一咧就係誒，我其實都好想了解下咧誒，洪律師嗰邊咧就係，如果你哋要搞呢個考試啦，你哋喺人力啊，即係其他方面係咪已經係準備好啊？嗰個方式係點樣做啊？即係我哋都想了解一下啦。誒，第二咧就係誒，其實都係可能係周生或者其他法學院。
啦，誒誒幾位嘅教授嘅professor都可以講下咧，就係誒係唔係誒覺得誒律師會佢誒誒舉辦咗呢個考試係可能係有對你哋現時即係喺誒P.C.L.L嗰個運作上咧係會有一啲你哋憂慮嘅。
第三咧就係據我所瞭解，我唔知道其他兩間學院，當然我我哋都有同事喺度，我院長都喺度。我我哋好似咧，我哋譬如城大咧，誒J.D.同埋LLB咧，佢入PCL嘅時候咧，佢係我哋係用翻佢自己LLB嗰度，佢就誒畫翻佢自己。
幾嗰個嗰個誒curve嘅，即係我哋誒嗰個誒計法，因為始終咧有誒嗰個J.D係兩第二個學位。我唔知其他誒法學院係咪噉，或者因為我唔係負責P.C，我就係有時聽到啲同事係噉樣同我講嘅。咁呢三樣嘢咧，可能都需要大家陣間包括埋你好想講嘅。
In
start going forward.
但係，我 think 我嘅 concern 是要 have。
我第二樣嘢，我想講講嘅咧，就係。
作為律師，或者有讀法律學位，然後入行成為律師或者律師，可以有。
一 pool of 1,200 students, two competing courses aiming at the same students. It
What I think would be interesting would be to be more radical and perhaps build on the discussion about legal executive training and think of a model where people who've been in the profession.
我哋覺得就最大嘅困難就係律師會咧，係冇冇一個進一步嘅消息畀任何人嘅。律師會佢以前做過consultation個報告咧，又係冇人知道嘅。
Speak to the microphone. Can you hear me? Thank you, Mr. Chairman. It's been interesting discussion, and of course, the number of PCL places and the ratio between those places and the job market are not really questions for the university as such.
埋佢係考嘅試A，亦都冇一個統一嘅評核。咁而家你整個LSE出嚟嘅時候，整多第四個出嚟。噉佢話佢要同呢呢piece睇齊，噉佢同邊一間睇齊咧？我哋又唔知。咁所以而家咧，我哋覺得而家就係阿洪律師呢個建議咧。
首先咧就係我哋話嗰個樽頸嘅地方嘅問題。咁當然嚟講咧，就呢個咧係一個政策嘅問題啦。究竟個樽頸嘅地方係應該唔緊要，我包埋樽頸嘅地方係應該喺一個係academic嘅時間，即係益轉。
基本教育而係未做呢個誒見習律師合約，或者未做大律師嘅學徒嗰陣時候啊，喺嗰個時候嚟定咧噉，還是最後咧應該由市場嚟定咧咁咁呢樣嘢咧係一個政策嘅問題咧，就每個人嘅睇法都唔同。但大律師嚟講咧，亦都係有個。
憂慮就係咁咧，就係當然喺我哋嗰個專家嘅報告度咧，佢話誒佢哋嘅得嘅資料咧，就係律師嘅誒B.C畢業嘅人，同埋攞到聘約嘅人咧，而家嘅比例咧大概係八十至九十嘅percent嘅。咁呢個咧，其
咁所以咧，即係成日都係有個噉嘅比例，所以我哋係有一個憂慮嘅就係，如果話律師嗰個途徑係太多嘅時候咧，就自然咧有多唔係好想做大律師嘅人咧，做夾硬去做大律師。咁呢方面咧對社會係唔好嘅。明白，聽得好清楚你嘅意見。誒，幾位啊？
我聽見，我聽見到咧，就係話要即係覺得要改變，唔好話有而家呢個三間大學有個三個唔同嘅PC個capital先啊！嗰個源罪就係話三間大學有唔同嘅招生系統又唔定，誒課程又未必相同，同埋。
咁而家到而家，律師會講嘅嘢，佢想點做咧，亦都唔知嘅。咁所以嚟講咧，我哋覺得喺噉嘅情形之下咧，要我哋話啊，要去support佢嘅時候咧，係有巨大嘅困難。Okay. Ah, maybe any professors from any law school would like to add that? Okay, Professor Howell, please. Yeah, thank you.
There must be a rationale why you would choose one course than the other, and simply because you can't get on to one course doesn't seem to be a good reason to create another course. Because if if that's the only reason for it, those people are going to be seen as the ones who didn't make it into the top flight, and that wouldn't be giving those people the best.
活躍的替代路徑入到 profession， which is distinct and different from the PCL and meets the needs of a different group of students. But to have the same course aimed at the same cohort of students doesn't seem to me to be the best use of our limited resources.好啊，對唔住，因為咧，我哋時間真係有有限，下一輪嘅。
嘅嘉賓亦都嚟咗。誒，我想睇下政府有冇誒任何你一定要補充嘅係好簡短嘅時間關係咧，係冇㗎啦。嚇，如果冇咧就誒噉樣噉啊。副主席亦都有一啲書面嘅問題啦，我亦都答應大家咧，我會係誒誒send畀大家啦。所以誒，if you have any further comments。
Please submit to our panel in writing. We will certainly consider all your views. Okay. Thank you all for your coming, because it's a very, very valuable time for us to understand the new proposal and all the the views of different universities. Thank you very much. Thank you.
嚇。
誒。
係咪呢個？
跟進誒法改會報告書嘅重要性嘅。
性罪行嗰度，你會唔會改嗰個去到再下一次會議啊？因為你而家已經係跳咗一。
齊保持香港嘅法律係與時並進，法律改革嘅工作咧，亦都係有賴呢個事務委員會同埋立法會同埋其他各國事務委員會嘅努力咧，先至可以順利進行嘅。
冇時間啊，係嘛？嚇嚇，係啊，因為你七點鐘完會啊嘛。我哋唔係，我哋都可以加多十五分鐘。我我同我我哋得啊嘛。可唔可以搬去下一個？可唔可以啊？好唔該曬你。
我哋要隨即即刻請我哋誒律政司司長啦，同埋係。即我咧就誒唔係呢個委會嘅委員啦，但係咧我係特登趕翻嚟咧，係想講即係item。誒，而家我哋即刻進入嘅。唔係我，但係你而家唔係去到落實香港法改委啊嘛？我係想講最後嗰個嗰個集控。
Thank you, thank you for coming。誒，亦都係好多謝啊律政司司長同埋專員。誒，今日咧就係我哋係而家去到咧，就係落實香港法律改革委員會提出嘅建議，相關嘅文件係C.B.括弧四一二四九stroke high誒十七-hyphen十八。
闕湖零五同埋闕湖零六嘅噉，由於咧，我哋今日嘅頭先剛才嗰個議題就啊討論好激烈，亦都即係代表嘅團體好多噉，就所以咧，而家我哋就啊都用啊用多咗時間啊，又停咗兩次會咧，因為要去隔離投票，所以我都啊。
誒吸納咗剛才啊個佩凡議員嘅意見，我哋係將啊，如果誒政府都OK咧，我哋都想將誒法改委最後嗰個啊議題，我哋咧就係啊可能要留到下一次睇下嗰個情況嘅。佢係升最後。
主席，誒或者就誒法會會下一個議題，關於兩個諮詢報告咧，因為佢哋有一個諮詢嘅時間性，其實都喺八月中，即係嗰個諮詢截止嘅，即係八月中或者誒中下旬噉樣。咁所以都有個時間。我哋儘量今日我哋嗱，我就可以有酌情權加多十五分鐘嘅。噉樣好。咁如果我哋委員同意，其實我哋再可以。
而家多十五分鐘嘅，噉就今次一次過，我哋係誒盡量傾咗佢。噉我諗咧時間誒即刻開始啦，好冇啊！首先我哋係誒請我哋嘅誒律政司司長鄭玉華資深大律師簡介文件。好誒，主席誒，今次係我首次根據呢個。
提交立法會。
亦都係六十四份報告書裏邊嘅四點七嘅percent。
就民事、刑事不同方面，誒涉及實體法同埋程序法咧，係提出咗改革嘅建議嘅。
第一類咧就係有三十五份報告書嘅建議咧，已經全部落實㗎啦。咁嗱，呢個佔咗大係五十四點七嘅百分比。
第二類咧就係有八份報告書嘅建議咧，已經獲得部分落實。呢個咧係六十四份報告書裏邊嘅十二點五嘅percent。
整體嚟講咧，喺過去一年落述落實法改會建議嘅工作咧，係有正面嘅進展，包括係以立法形式落實若干建議。
相關嘅法例咧，能反映爭議解決業界嘅最新發展嘅趨勢，增強香港作為跨境投資同埋商業爭議解決中心嘅競爭力。
咁而家咧，誒政府咧正係研究同埋誒研究呢個諮詢嘅結果，律政司咧係計劃喺二零一八一九年度嘅立法會會期咧，將呢個條例草案提交立法會。
嘅草稿咧，展開咗公眾諮詢，亦都喺二零一八年一月咧就向呢誒本事務委員會咧係簡報有關嘅諮詢，諮詢期咧亦都喺二零一八年嘅四月底咧係結束嘅。
第三類咧就係十五份嘅報告書嘅建議咧，就係喺獲考慮或者喺落實誒誒誒之中嘅。咁呢個咧就係我哋報告書裏邊嘅二十三點四嘅percent。
喺呢六十五份報告書裏邊咧，有一份報告書建議咧係對誒誒有一份報告書建議對法律唔作改變，其餘六十四份嘅報告書咧嘅落實情況咧可以分為五個大嘅類別。
事務委員會喺二零一二年嘅建議定立嘅機制咧，以法改法律改革委員會主席嘅身份咧，向呢個事務委員會匯報法改會嘅建議嘅落實嘅情況嘅。作為律政司司長同埋法改會嘅主席咧，我有責任咧，同埋相關嘅政策局同埋部門咧，係一。
誒，中審法院首席法官同埋法改會嘅成員，同埋我自己本人咧，誒，不但好重視挑選合適嘅課題畀法改會去考慮咧，同時我哋亦都係持續向政府相關嘅決策局同埋部門咧，強調回應誒，同埋跟。
主席同埋各位委員，誒因應已收到一份今次會議討論嘅資料文件，呢份文件咧列出咗法改會喺一九八二年發表第一份報告書以後，誒誒誒以嚟嘅每份報告書嘅落實嘅詳情。法改會合共發發表咗咧六十五份報告書。
而第三、誒第四類咧，就係有三份報告書，佢嘅建議咧就係唔獲得政府接納嘅。咁呢個咧係六十四份報告書裏邊嘅四點七嘅percent。而第五類咧，就係政府就住三份報告書嘅建議咧，係表示無意喺現階段落實。咁呢個咧。
法改會同埋我本人咧，都十分重視報告書嘅建議，能唔能夠獲得有效噉樣落實？
誒，再者咧，喺呢啲進度報告咧，亦都會上載到法改會嘅網站，等公眾咧係可以查閲嘅。
法例草案委託書目標係希望喺二零一八一九年嘅立法年度咧嘅會期期間咧，可以將呢個條例草案提交立法會嘅。
律政司亦都正正咧，係就二零一二年二月發表嘅一罪兩審報告書草擬條例草案咧，係以便徵詢法律專業團體、司法機構同埋其他持份者嘅意見。
噉我知道係嗰個會議都開咗廿幾次，噉我想問啫，具體嚟講咧，你覺得即係嗯客觀啲嚟睇，你覺得幾時會可以有到一啲成績出嚟畀大家去再跟進啊？司長請。
已經差唔多係誒完成嗰個相關嗰個文件嘅起草啦，中英等等噉，所以我相信好快。具體嘅時間咧，我哋誒冇一個好具體嘅時間，我可以誒講到出嚟噉嘅。
舉例講啦，立法會喺二零一七年六月十四日咧就通過咗《二零一七年仲裁及調解法例第三者資助修訂條例》，落實咗二零一六年十月發表嘅第三方資助仲裁報告書，令到相。
為咗落實二零零九年八月發表嘅刑事法律程序中全民證據嘅報告書，律政司喺二零一七年四月二十一日發表咗誒諮詢文件，而徵詢法律團體嘅誒徵詢法律專業團體司法。
機構同埋其他持份者嘅意見諮詢期咧，亦都喺二零一七年七月三十一日咧已經做完㗎啦。咁律政司咧已經考慮咗諮詢嘅結果，進一步完完善相關嘅條例草案。誒預計咧喺二零一八年七月初咧係將條例草案咧係。
另外咧，喺落實二零一一年七月發表嘅持久授權書個人照顧事宜嘅報告書，律政司喺召開跨部門工作小組嘅會議，檢討報告書嘅建議之後咧，喺二零一七年十二月底咧，就住條例草案嘅。
另外，就落實法改會於一九九六年十月發表嘅《無力償還第二部分企業拯救及無力償債情況下營商嘅報告書》咧，財經事務及副務局咧已經發出誒，已經發出咗。
法改會每次開會落實嘅進度咧，都一定係會議嘅議程上邊。另外咧，法改會同政府各各個相關嘅決決策局嘅部同埋部門咧，係一直有一定嘅聯繫，要求佢哋咧係提交最新嘅落實嘅進度報告。
我哋會繼續同法改會嘅成員咧，本住事務委員會同埋立法會其他各事務委員會合作，一同監察落實嘅進度。最後，我希望藉呢個機會咧，亦都感謝呢個委員會同埋立法會誒所有嘅成員一直對法改會嘅工作嘅關心同埋支持。
好多謝主席。好多謝律政司司長。誒，黃秘書長會唔會有任何嘅補充？好啦，多謝主席。好噉，跟住咧就係委員發問嘅時間。而家咧，我哋先有三位委員咯，每一位委員係四分鐘。誒，首先係阿莫乃光議員。係唔該誒，其實我唔係委員添啊，即係不過就係。
要求啦。
所以我哋都盡量去配合，咁整體嗰個整體研究咧，係要有啲時間再睇一睇先知道。好，跟住咧就係何君瑤議員。
另外一啲法例咧都好重要，譬如好似集體訴訟啊，郭榮亨議員剛才提出，咁呢個我哋應該要做就做啦，噉就要早啲要畀個決定。第三咧，我見到益權。
有噉嘅，即係有噉嘅指標咧。呢個第一點，我我提出嚟，因為而家嚟講就好唔清晰。第二個咧，就有啲快起上嚟咧。如果你嘅即係有需要要要踩油嘅，噉我諗我哋即係就住環境，我哋都會配合。
噉樣，二零零二年做咗報告，等喺度，一路都晾喺度，都未做。咁究竟我哋做定唔做咧？但係我見到佢係屬於係正在考慮，或者誒在研究當中。咁二零零二年到二零一六年已經十六，即係一八年有十六年時間。
誒多謝啊！主席畀我誒先問一條問題誒。其實我都好簡單，就係關心到嗰個檔案法同埋誒公開資料嗰個法例嘅喺法改會入邊嗰個嘅工作。咁因為我都好記得，即係舊年就好似話今年年初會有個報告，咁今年年初又話可能年中會。
會有噉，但係就仲未知道誒，會唔會講講嗰個進度係點咧？因為之前就係聽到有即係應該已經差唔多㗎啦。咁誒，可唔可以請司長可以講講畀我哋聽，而家情況係點咧？唔該，主席。係司長請。誒，其實就住嗰兩個誒報告咧，其實已經係誒已。
係，黃黃秘書長。之內可以誒將有關嘅誒諮詢文件咧係誒出台嘅，因為而家去到一個即係尾段嘅階段，無論喺好似誒律政司司長指出，即係無論係文件嘅整理方面咧，同埋翻譯嘅工作，我哋都去到一個好啊，即係後嘅階段噉樣。唔好意思，頭先聽唔清楚話幾多之內話。誒，今年之內嘅。今年之內。
內OK好，好，今年之內，噉我希望快一啲咧，因為等咗一段時間，因為之後若果再要做諮詢啊，嗰樣嘢都仲要仲就算，即使如果你嘅建議係即係呢方面會做啲立法工作嘅話，都有排諮詢，希望可以儘量快啲開始嗰個工作。唔該，主席。好，咁冇跟進咧，就係阿郭榮亨議員。主席誒，我。
我都同莫乃光議員一樣啦，非常關心呢個檔案法嘅啊一個，因為我哋共同都有一個啊私人條例草案係講呢一件事。咁政府既然肯做咧，我哋都希希望落結快啲成事嘅。呢個亦都係特首嘅一個承諾啦。咁誒，司長，你知我好關心呢一個集體訴訟class action呢一樣嘢。
誒呢個誒集體訴訟呢一個問誒呢一件事情咧，其實係嗰個工作小組同埋小組嘅委員會咧都開過誒二十二同埋二十八次嘅會議。咁誒政府咧而家係等緊小組委員會嘅一個報告，有咗個報告之後咧，佢哋就會積極噉樣去。
研究嘅，咁所以因為佢涉及嘅有一啲技術性嘅問題咧，佢哋係需要花一啲時間，咁所以我暫時畀唔到一個好具體嘅時間畀你，誒會係幾時會有一個誒東西可以出嚟畀我哋再跟進。好，係噉啊，即係我期待，即係希望可以盡快啦，因為呢個都係法律。
界，尤其是法律界同埋，即係啊，一般市民都關心嘅一個問題。咁第二樣嘢就係，我想知道，即係嗯喺仲裁方面啦，知道司長你係都好關心呢個議題。你覺得而家法改委啊，法改會係咪應該就住譬如啊，我哋講嘅誒有條件收費啊等等嘅呢啲？
問題咧就住啊，仲裁就住仲裁，即係唔係其他嘅一般訴訟，係咪都適合去做一個即係諮詢或者再研究一下咧？現階段司長，多謝議員呢條問題。誒呢個呢個建議咧，喺我哋有個Advisory Committee for Arbitration咧，亦都有人提出嚟噉。
所以我哋先會喺Guidance Committee嗰度討論一下，先至決定應該下一步點樣做。好，誒，我最後一個問題嘅就係之前你上一手啊，袁國強司長咧，佢都講過話就希望將法改會嘅啊秘書處同埋員工咧係啊更加專業化，即係話係有係咪可以近去考慮有一。
啲全職嘅專業嘅啊法律研究人員咧，係可以喺嗰度噉就唔係淨係單靠。當然有好多好好嘅法律界嘅學者啊、律師大律師係願意付出佢哋嘅時間啦。咁但係同時間啊，可唔可以有資源畀法改會做，變成一個更加專業嘅一個基？
司長喺現時律政司嗰個資源嘅運用下邊咧，我哋亦都係注意到法改委嘅法改會嘅工作咧係非常之誒繁重嘅，因為除咗佢誒去協助小組委員會去做個報告之外咧，佢亦都要相關誒嘅激誒政策局咧係要係要作一個誒聯絡啊等等。
咁多嘅議題係咪真係即係需要更多嘅資源，即係誒畀到一個計劃畀我哋拎嚟呢個委員會，大家都係願意跟進嘅。
係，多謝主席。啊，司長啊，就法改會嘅工作咧，就似乎忙，又好似唔係好忙。八二年到現在咧，都已經三十六年，就做咗六十五個嘅嗰個報告。誒，完成率咧就有三十五個，但係大部分好多都係已經係舊嘅嘢，有啲可能急起上嚟，譬如好似阿。
Third-party分離咧啊，噉啊就住香港環境裏邊咧就加快步伐。我睇到，我想提出一樣嘢，即係而家呢個噉嘅報告睇上嚟有少少misleading，因為你六十五個裏邊你三十幾年噉，我都唔知邊個同邊個嘅時間裏邊即係嗰個速度係點樣。有啲快起上嚟就好快，有啲咧，譬如好似debt collection。
都係時候應該，如果做咗報告，係咪應該會有個benchmark？你哋有performance pledge，就會話當LSC即係誒呢一個誒law reform啊，law L R C law reform commission做完啲嘢出嚟嘅時候，作為政府係咪應該要指定時間？譬如五年內要決定去馬定唔去馬，係咪應該要？
逆權侵佔啊，第五十八項嗰個，你哋應該都係話在考慮當中啦。呢一個香港咧，係土地嘅資為重要，但係逆權侵佔裏邊咧產生到好多嘅民間嘅矛盾。點解你會可以客家白即係變地主？即係我咁咁辛苦又擁有笪地，我買到。
翻到嚟，但係你已經即係佔咗個便宜，唔畀租金啊！我有陣時睇唔到啊嘛，老虎都會瞌眼瞓㗎。但係你霸咗十二年之後咧，我我就釘你唔到。噉我覺得呢一個咧就係好唔唔配合呢一個社會嘅世情。會唔會喺呢一方面嚟講又加快咧？我即係提出。
兩個具具具體嘅嗰個方向要睇，誒law誒law reform commission做完嘅嘢係有冇指標幾時答話去片唔去片？第二有啲可能仲要快，要要要要加油嘅，譬如好似疫權侵侵佔會唔會提要要提一提速咧？嗯，係司長誒。
多謝議員嘅問題。誒，首先注誒，首先第一個可唔可以有一個具體嘅指標咧？咁其實咧喺二零一一年十月嘅時期咧，誒，我哋亦都係誒做咗一個嘅架構咧，就係希望十二每喺喺十二個報告書出咗十二個月之內咧，誒相關嘅政策局咧就會明確。
學噉樣去講，佢究竟會接受或者唔接受嗰個報告書嘅嘢。假如佢做唔到咧，我哋希望佢六個月之內咧，亦都做一個interim report畀我哋有一個時間表。咁呢個咧，我哋亦都係一路噉樣係跟進緊嘅。咁當然喺二零一二年嘅時候，亦都加落咗另外而家我今次過嚟做一個報告嘅。
個制度咁希望咧係就住落述嘅情落實嘅情況咧係具體化。誒第二點誒個bench mark嗰度咧係誒我相信係有一定嘅難度嘅，因為每一個政策局佢就住佢佢某一啲嘅誒報告書裏邊嘅建議，佢應該會有優先同埋誒相關嘅考慮。
資源啊，分配嘅考慮噉，所以佢去實際幾時落實咧，係可能係要就住唔同嘅情況嚟做噉，所以好難係具體話有一個誒時間點係可以誒全部係誒誒一貫都用嘅。咁第三個頭先提到某一個，請請司長繼續。
第三個提到某一個誒誒議案啊，某一個報告書幾時要落實，係咪可以快啲慢啲咧？噉係好係好需要。正如我頭先回覆嘅第二點噉樣樣，係睇嗰個政策局佢係要點樣樣去安排。咁有一啲我哋能盡快做到嘅，我哋都一定係會誒盡快去做嘅。
咁至於最最或者我最尾補充埋嘅就係睇到嘅時間點嗰度咧，其實喺附件嗰度咧，議員可以睇到嗰個報告書係幾時出，然之後咧嗰個相關做咗嘅工作嗰個時間點都喺個附件嗰度寫明咗啦。多謝主席。好，多謝司長。啊，跟住我嘅時間啦。咁第一咧，我就。
都希望喺呢度on record跟進翻咧，即係二十段講嗰個啊纏繞行為嗰個嘅誒立法嘅跟進啦。即係事實上，我都記得有啲記者啊、藝人啦，甚至係好多名人啦，咁都可能會有呢一種嘅遭遇。噉就誒，我希望就即係唔好擺咗入。
exposure.
necrophilia。
咁誒，應該就係誒。
voyeurism, bestiality.
acts done with an intention to commit a sexual offence.
on the matter of miscellaneous sexual offences.
I'm pleased to be able to present to you our consultation paper.
今日最後一個議程咧，就係啊香港法律改革。
它 covers a number of miscellaneous sexual offences, such as incest.
誒，其實而家未開始計鐘嘅，請誒誒嗰個行政人員刪咗嗰個計時器先嚇。
八就係誒，我哋誒，關於諮詢民警嘅雜要噉就請委員有興趣嘅咧，都可以按樓發言啦。
This paper was published in May and it is the third and the final part of our overall review of substantial substantive sexual offences.
咁而家咧，我就首先請誒政府嘅誒誒法律改革委員會嘅誒代表咧，係誒先發表意見嘅。
The first one to speak, I suppose, should be Mr. Peter Duncan. See, thank you very much. May you start to present your ideas. Thank you very much, Madam Chairman, and good evening to you and to members of your panel.
雪櫃，你哋呢度都有講話會參考下海外嘅做法，嚇噉我希望咧係一個誒，你哋會跟進嘅議題。咁第二個咧就係誒頭先啊何議員都有提啊，逆權侵佔咧，我哋喺呢個委員會都討論過幾次，好詳細嘅。噉啊誒瞌眼瞓當然有啦，如果如果太誒好多好多單位。
噉佢會瞌眼瞓，唔記得咗。但係我哋咧就喺地區見得好多，有啲係反為係啲長者長者，佢可能係得誒多一間屋嚟收租，佢交咗畀啲誒親戚朋友代佢收租收收下，噉就可能出現咗誒亦僱亦權侵佔佢係唔知咁呢啲就比較值得同情嘅個案。咁所以我覺得都係有。
需要睇點樣可以取得個平衡嘅嚇，有一啲咧佢又好即係係壘權咗喺嗰個地方好多年。我哋點樣取得呢個平衡？我覺得係係應該係值得研究咯嚇。你即係兩邊咧，佢都有一個誒例句喺度嘅。我我覺得委員會係需要跟進，同埋希望政府繼續跟進。
第三方面咧就係誒，秘書長又啱喺度啦。噉啊，我就即係誒好多謝誒，即係阿袁國強誒前司長佢提到你哋資源啦。即係頭先啊，副主席都係跟住問題，想問下秘書長誒，即係你點樣睇喺法改委要即係跟住我哋咁多議員社會噉。
多謝主席。係律政司司長指出，誒有關嘅資源嗰個誒加強嗰度咧，其實確實我哋係睇到有個需要喺度。我亦都瞭解到，舊年十二月誒，議員們都係好支持我哋喺個秘書處嗰個誒人手安排上高，希望能夠加強，以致我哋可以喺整理有關嘅報告書方面咧，係可以加大。
力度嘅噉，所以嚟緊，我哋其實政府內部喺律政司嗰方面，尤其是啦，係會誒作出一啲適當嘅配合，睇下究竟喺人手上應該點樣加強啦噉樣。咁當然喺上次嗰個討論當中，亦都有提到就係另一個方法咧，就話將有關嘅研究咧係可以外判畀一啲專家去跟進嘅。咁呢個亦都係喺我哋。
考慮之內嘅，多謝主席。好，師長會唔會仲有補充？我頭先睇嘅冇諗過。係噉，即係就誒，如果大家都認為誒都算即係將自己興趣嘅問咗咧，我哋就誒誒結束呢一個議題。噉就誒隨即咧，我哋就會係誒轉落去誒。
誒委員會係佢舉手下一個應該嚇，集項性罪行諮詢文件同埋人身傷害個案按期支付未來金錢損害賠款嘅諮詢文件嘅。咁因為呢一個咧係有一個時間性喺度，政府亦都有做諮詢，噉我希望大家亦都。
都係誒，湧入表達你哋嘅意見啦。咁咧就誒相關嘅文件係C.B.括弧四一一零九stroke十七-hyphen十八括弧零一括弧零二同埋括弧零七咧，就係人身傷害個案嗰個賠誒損失賠償嘅諮詢文件，仲有就係括弧零。
基於性傾向。
Turning to the creation, the proposed creation of a new offence of voyeurism.
There are some issues which arise from our consideration of that offence.
例如，whether it should be confined to sexual intercourse.
Moving from incest, we've proposed the creation of a new offence of sexual exposure.
我們有建議那被保留，但係那元素那個 offence 應該被 reform。
或 whether it should be extended beyond that to other forms of sexual activity between close relatives.
和審查一些同性戀罪行，仍屬我們的法律範疇。
這是要區分從現有的誹謗罪，即係不當暴露，係一個公眾秩序罪。
this is to cover that sort of activity, where the object is to target a specific person.
第二，個問題就係，是否應該擴展到非血緣父母，即係説養父母。
或 for to threaten that person or to alarm that person, or to obtain sexual gratification for that sort of activity.
我會快速過一過主要的特別 offence，我們建議的。第一個是姦淫。
第三ly， it should be in our view be extended to blood relatives such as blood uncles and aunts not covered by the current legislation.
這些反映我們的總體做法，四個原則：，保護原則、性別中立、尊重個人的性自主，以及避免任何區別。
Apart from making some recommendations to reform some of the current existing sexual offences, the subcommittee is also recommending introducing a number of specific new specific sexual offences.
yeah。
OK，ready嘛？
We.
Now I would like to in.
Okay, so how about the others?
應該被 entitled to privacy in those circumstances.
And we've recommended changes in the law to cover that.
The consultation paper was published on the 25th of April 2018.
And then finally, as I mentioned, there are a number of existing homosexual sexual offences still on our statute books, and we believe that they should be removed.
啊，nothing for yet. Okay, so啊，maybe啊，now，yeah，係嗰個批文嗰度啊，即係因為我哋一問咧，我哋就即刻問埋兩個問題啊嘛，好嘛？好，好得。Okay，唔該你。嗯。
There are a number of offences with regard to the acts done with intention to commit a sexual offence, not would perhaps not be caught by the common law concept of an attempt.
主席，係啦，請你講。And members of the panel, thank you for the opportunity for me to come to discuss with you the topic of periodical payment for future pecuniary loss in personal injury cases.
bestiality， I think the proposals for that are self-explanatory。 necrophilia， surprising to many， is not currently an offence in Hong Kong， and we believe the time has come for that to be legislated。
考慮到，應該有立法來覆蓋非同意的觀察或視覺錄影，另一人，再次為性目的，而該另一人有權相信他或她。
So, Madam Chairman and members of the panel, that's a very brief but hopefully helpful introduction to the matters that we've covered in our in our consultation paper. And my colleagues, myself, would be very happy to answer any questions that you may have. Okay. So.
Any any further presentations? Not not yet. Yeah. So I would like to introduce Mr Nicholas Pyre from the Bar Association. May you take up the speech now? Well, I have nothing to add about the sexual offences. I'm concerned about payment today. Okay.
the the presumed rate of return of
Investment， which is an element in the assessment of future loss in PI cases。
如果賠償金額未計息，受傷方會被過度賠償。
一 particular matter that is closely related to periodic co-payment is the fixing of the discount rate.
introduce and to order payment of damages for future loss by way of a periodic payment order.
if necessary, including the viability and desirability of having a mechanism to decide.
實質上，那意味著賠償金額將會在審判時或和解時一次結清。
If the amount of damages that is to be incurred in the future to cover losses or future or expenses to be incurred in the future,
在最近的陳柏棠，由巴瓦尼大法官審理的案件中，他引述英國的經驗，以《1996年損害法》第2條為例，這條文在經過幾次的修改後，
太高或太低，和因此，傳統的approach to quantify future losses by using the multiplier and multiplier model, as established by case law, has been generally criticised as being imprecise and unscientific.
Those advising the parties in a settlement has to be arrived at following the principle of restitutio in integrum， meaning that as far as money can buy， the injured person would be put or restored in the circumstances where he had not suffered the injury.
The impetus for the study on the topic was because in 2015, after a decision in the High Court, the Secretary for Justice and the Chief Justice tasked the Law Reform Commission to look into this topic of payment.
或未來 pecuniary loss in personal injury cases to see if any reform is needed, so as to allow the introduction of periodical payment for payment of future pecuniary losses in PI cases, and to make appropriate recommend.
傳統上，作為法律，兩種特殊損害，那意味著損害發生在判決或和解之前，以及未來的損失和費用。那意味著判決後的費用，作為由法官在審判中預測的。
And history and experience will tell us that such an approach, which is basically by applying a multiplier to a multiplicand in arriving at a lump sum, would invariably be inaccurate in the sense that it can only be either.
reform has come to the stage since 2005 that the court, despite the views of the parties, would, in the circumstances which is deemed to be in the best interests of the parties and for the proper administration of justice, to
是的。
Rate of discount.
And therefore, there has to be a discount rate to be applied.
aspect of whether periodical payment should be introduced in the.
The third questioned for public consultation.
There are a number of questions identified in the consultation paper in respect of which we solicit the opinion of the public.
on the amount of damages to be received in PI cases, and therefore the subcommittee also looked into the viability and desirability of introducing a mechanism for fixing the discount rate.
It is noteworthy that in this particular consultation paper, the questions identified are framed in an open manner, so as to engender comprehensive discussion on the topic.
situation where the consent of the party is not forthcoming, and also whether there should be any limit to the type of case or specific criteria for deciding the situation where a court can impose a periodic payment order.
那係一個 perennial 問題，和如指出由 Mr Justice Bhawani 在陳百強案中，個個個別原告唔會有資源，而事實上，係唔有利於公正司法的行政，有個別當事人去動員資源去辯論。
Question one, basically. Sorry, Mr. Lund, I need to inform the panel. I have to exercise my discretion to extend fifteen minutes, and if necessary, we may extend more with the consent of the members present. It depends on how many.
多少個問題，和多少成員會跟進這個議題？好，所以梁先生，請繼續。在利益時間，我會非常簡短地回答這個問題，因為它已經非常詳細地在諮詢文件中説明瞭。
The first question is whether or not, as a matter of principle, the court should be invested with the power to order periodical payment for future pecuniary loss in the personal injury cases. The second question is whether.
或 not a mechanism should be introduced for the fixing and reviewing of discount rates, and if so, who would be the authority to fix the discount rate, and what are the interest party or stakeholders who should be consulted during this periodical review?
Question four concerns the circumstances under which the court may review periodic payment order in related contingencies, and whether the current regime of awarding provisional damages should coexist with the periodic payment order regime. The
嗯。
The.
The。
通常要買一間平。
And they're not long-term insurance.
They don't have long-term insurance registration.
first of all, the security issue is a big problem because
另一個我認為係一個實用嘅一個，大多數原告喺香港想將損害收在自己嘅手裡。
在U.K.， most of the accident that involve PPOs are motor insurance cases.
所以我們有 dealt with funding options， and I think this is a major problem which has not been considered, which will be considered by the insurers.
So far as the medical insurers are concerned, they're not onshore in Hong Kong either. So that is an issue which would have to be covered.
The consultation period will last until the 24th of August, and we look forward to receiving the submissions from all stakeholders and interested parties.
Okay, thank you, Mr.梁。Any additional comments from the bar? No。我諗而家咧就係我哋委員嘅時間。Two things I would like to point out。In my the bar's response。
of securing the payment, so as to ensure that the receiving party, the injured person, would have the stream of payment secured and would not be exposed to further uncertainties.
所以他們會 seek in any event probably to capitalise their payment with a third party， and that is why we've suggested a third fund for someone like the MIB to administer. Then you don't need to deal with the security of payment issue.
And secondly, in Hong Kong, probably most of our cases will be construction site cases or damaged babies with cerebral palsy. Those insurers are not long-term insurers registered under our insurance companies ordinance.
Last question concerns the issue of security of payment under periodic payment order, and the stakeholder, in particular the insurance industry, are welcome to explore the various modes.
number and it would seem much better to if the government would.
consider funding, say a third fund for MIB or someone else to administer. That would solve a number of those problems.
court of protection, something like that, or another institution to pay for these things when there is an unknown.
修定噉，我哋都係贊成嘅。噉我有一誒，我唯一有一個保留嘅地方咧，就係關於亂倫嗰邊。
所以我們有，一個未知數量的人民可能想要PPOs，和是，值唔值設立？
在有關住户內生活及相對於一名兒童而言，處於受信任或權威地位的其他人。
父母，你哋認為係唔需要喺呢度誒擺入去咧？咁噉，我亦都留有留意你哋文件嗰度嘅誒諮詢文件嘅第一點一白同埋一。
Thank you. Okay, thank you, Mr. Perrie. 啊，跟住係我哋委員嘅發問，而家暫時有三位，每一位咧就係四分鐘連問連答嘅。第一位係黃碧雲議員。
點一零一咧，嗰度咧，你哋係有引英國嘅檢討小組嘅，咁嗰度咧就講緊咧，誒英國嘅檢討小組咧就講各項新罪行嘅範圍應該擴大，去到涵蓋。
因為他們需要某處住，和在現有的法律下，案件是Robertson Johnson，他們只會獲得一筆兩百萬的兩百分之一的樓盤資產價值。所以，會有很少的申請人申請。
動或者畀公眾嘅觀感會覺得咧，如果係繼父母或者寄養父母咧，就唔算係亂倫啦。咁咁呢個信息如果出咗去咧，我哋誒民主黨係好擔心嘅。咁所以我想聽一聽政府嗰個考慮係點啊？好，政府邊一位？
誒，多謝主席。誒，首先咧就多謝誒法改會幫我哋做咗呢份文件啦。噉我都誒民主黨好詳細咁睇咗一次。咁誒大致上誒對你哋提嘅建議咧，我哋都係誒支持嘅。特別係嗰啲關於性罪行誒無分性別嘅嗰個噉樣嘅。
嘅誒，你哋嘅建議，噉你哋有諮詢咧喺建議一嗰度咧，係講緊新罪行應唔應該涵蓋領養父母？噉我見你哋嘅文件咧，其實你哋都誒似乎係誒同意應該係要包領養父母，噉我哋都係贊成呢一個安排嘅。不過咧，我就見到似乎。
乎咧，你哋對於領養父母同埋繼父母同埋寄養父母之間咧，你哋似乎係有唔同嘅對待嘅，即係你就覺得誒傾向咧，領養父母可能係可以包落去亂倫罪嗰度，但係咧繼父母同寄養父母咧，你哋就話佢哋因為冇血緣關係。
同埋已經有其他嘅刑事罪行條文可以保護兒童，咁咧就唔唔認為應該要將繼父母同寄養父母納入去嘅。咁其實誒，如果你講有冇血緣關係咧，領養父母都係冇血緣關係嘅。咁所以我想問就係點解會將誒繼父母同寄養？
咁所以無論係誒，如果從呢一個即係英國檢討少咗嗰個建議咧，咁領養父母、繼父母同寄養父母都係同兒童係住喺同一個住户嘅單位裏邊嘅。噉我想問你哋而家呢個建議將佢哋分開嚟噉樣對待，其實係咪會產生一個漏？
程序你係領養有機構係核准個領養，而實際上咧有啲嘅情況咧，可能嗰個細路都唔知道嗰個領養父母，可能佢以為佢係真係親生嘅。
都希望政府可以將我哋，如果可能係過咗期之後九月召開嘅公聽會嘅意見咧，都納入今次嘅誒諮詢過程嗰個裏邊嚇。
樣嘢，佢反而係大家同住之間嗰種可能出現一啲嘅濫用嘅情況，係去成噉樣。但係一聯鄰聚咧，個基礎咧就係話咧係涵蓋咧，即使。
嗰個所謂誒，即係即係誒，即係另外一人咧，係已經係成年人，兩個成年人都好啦。其實如果係亂倫罪涵蓋嘅時候咧，佢哋都一有性關係咧，都係一個罪行嚟嘅。噉啊，所以我哋要好小心咧，唔好係過分去將佢擴展。呢個係我哋嗰個基本嗰個嘅考慮咯。
會回應係張大明先生係誒就呢方面嗰個當然咧，我哋而家仲係諮詢期間咧，就係雖然我哋有一個初步嘅建議，但係我哋樂意係聽唔同嘅意見。所以今日咧，主要係想解釋翻我哋嗰個即係一啲嘅諗法噉樣，就唔係我哋最終嗰個睇法嚟嘅。噉我哋誒之前嘅諗法咧。
主要咧就係領養父母同埋繼父母或者寄養父母咧，最主要嗰個法律上嘅分別咧，就因為領養父母咧，基本上咧喺法律上咧，其實佢係承擔咗所有嘅所謂嘅權利同責任嘅，同嗰個兒童之間，甚至咧，因為佢係一個經過一個正式嘅程。
噉嘅情況咧，同繼父母係唔同。即係繼父母咧，只不過係因為咧係誒，即係有一個人可能同一個原本有仔女嘅人結婚，噉佢就即係我哋中華噉啊，成咗繼養父母啦。但係可能佢甚至係冇乜來往啊，冇乜關係啊，剩啊噉樣，噉佢亦都冇話一定係有一個正式嘅全面嘅。
法律責任咁呢個同寄養父母，如果係寄養父母咧，其實法律上我所瞭解咧，係都冇一個好明確嘅定義咩叫寄養父母，即係有時好短暫，你寄養佢喺度一段時間啊，成噉樣，咁咧就所以好快嘅原因咧，就係因為咧，我哋而家建議嘅亂倫罪咧，同英國係唔同，即係英國基本上佢唔係有亂倫罪嗰。
誒嗱，由於呢個討論咧都幾誒都有委員咧誒有興趣㗎。嗱，我諗咧就誒我咧就係要求得到大家嘅同意啦。我哋啊延到七點半嚇，咁盡量畀所有嘅委員咧係誒問連問連答嚇。咁咧就第二位嘅委員係阿陳志全議員。
係誒唔該，主席，我有誒一個意見，兩個問題嘅。首先咧，個意見就係應該要同主席你講嘅。我希望咧，本事務委員會咧就集控性罪行嘅諮詢文件咧，可以召開公聽會。但係我知道咧係有少少難度嘅，因為呢份文件五月係交出嚟，六月咧先至。
yeah。
邊位係張達明先生？
唔該，係誒，發舉委。
哋嗰個採用嘅原則啊，整體方向咯，啊，因為好多承諾嘅嘢都係要最後都唔係我哋執行嘅。
Mr. Chairman, I'm trying to respond to that, given the Chinese language implications. Thank you. Okay.
排到上我哋事務委員會，噉我哋七月尾有休會啦啊。噉我唔知我哋七月裏邊可唔可以安排到時間做？咁如果唔得嘅話，誒，其實呢一個諮詢，其實過去政府嘅諮詢咧都有時會延展佢諮詢期嘅。我唔知今次佢哋有冇考慮過啦。另外，如果唔得嘅話，噉。
第二個問題咧就嚟啦，我我係想問第七章嘅就係有關檢討一啲同啊同性戀或者關乎同性嘅肛交同嚴重威脅作為嘅現有罪行嘅。首先我要指出咧喺諮詢文件裏邊咧對同性戀呢個概念嘅運用咧個中英文咧係有所混淆。
嘅好似第七章嘅標題噉樣啦，就係檢討一些同性或關乎同性的膠膠，但係個英文咧就係review of some existing homosexual or homosexual related。所以如果係要表達同性homosexual咧，應該係同性戀，而唔應該咧就噉。
亦做檢討一些有關同性嘅現有罪行。咁喺文文件裏邊咧，有唔同嘅位，有時你哋就會用同性戀，有時咧就會簡單用同性嘅。咁呢個我希望你哋未來喺誒表述嘅時候咧，要一指一啲，因為英文嘅時候咧，你哋都係用誒同性戀誒homosexual。
sexual呢個字嘅我嘅問題就係咧，今次我知道第七章要誒將建議將一一八B、一一八G、一一八J、一一八K有關誒男同性之間嘅肛交罪行咧，就予以廢除，達至咧無分性別，尊重唔同性傾向嘅目標。但係咧，我見到餘下仲有。
有一啲誒法例，例如一一八C、一一八D、一四一B、一四一C呢啲部分咧，其實都係裏邊有性別元素同埋有關剛交嘅罪行咧。今次係冇足及嘅，譬如女童嘅法定剛交年齡咧，仍然保持喺二十一歲。咁同法改會第一本嘅誒性罪。
罪行改革嘅時候，要求唔分性別同埋性傾向嘅罪行咧，好似唔係咁一致噉樣。我想知我頭先提出嗰啲仍然有性別元素同埋誒嗰個年齡啊，唔唔唔同嘅法改會會唔會喺呢一次誒裏邊去做埋，定係會未來先至做咧噉樣？另外第二個問題咧就係。
有關誒判刑嘅問題，因為判刑嘅標準咧就會係第四份諮詢文件咧先至交代嘅。但係由於法改會計劃喺前三份文件推出之後咧，就會推出一份綜合報告嘅，所以有團體擔心前三份文件冇提及罪行同埋相關嘅判刑會受到忽略，就指。
法改會未來誒可同埋擔心誒男男男女嘅性罪行嘅定罪標準唔一致，咁誒政府可唔可以向即係大家保證喺第四策嘅時候檢討，會保證唔會因為性傾向而被判更重嘅刑罰咧？即係好似過去我哋法例裏邊存在嗰啲問題噉樣。
誒，我諗好快回應咧。當然有一啲咧，可能我都唔係可以好答得到嘅，就係誒中文嘅翻譯嗰度咧。好坦白講咧，就係誒我哋做嘅做，我哋用英文去做咗咧，跟住交畀專業嘅翻譯人員咧係去做咧，我哋就冇乜特別審議嘅。噉啊，陳議員嗰個我諗佢哋會再即係睇睇個表達嗰度啦。噉啊，至於誒另。
另外嗰個問題咧，就關於係誒另外一啲嘅即係罪行嗰度有性別同埋個唔同，係啦，唔均稱。嗱誒都誒，請坐啦。我可能我唔知秘書處可能提一提我咧，因為誒我印象之中咧，我哋最初咧其實誒嗰個最初嘅報告書話咧，我哋嘅誒諮詢文。
嘅裏面咧，第一嚟講，我哋都好清楚定立咗一個嘅原則咧，係唔應該係有一個所謂誒性傾向嗰方面嘅歧視啊或嘅性嘅咁咧就誒，至於因為今次我只係我哋係羅列緊咧係取消嗰啲咧係因為咧《殘抗性罪行》咧，我哋會睇到就係呢樣違反咗一樣嘢。譬如陳議員提到咧。
多謝。誒，跟住咧就係阿郭榮亨議員。
都希望能夠平衡到即係社會嘅利益同埋咧嗰啲誒新鎖人嘅利益噉。好，唔該曬主席。
咁其實呢個折扣率呢個問題咧，就遠遠超出咗按期支付未來金錢損失賠款制度呢個範疇。
會傾嘅，噉我希望咧大家能夠真係，因為保險就係一個最重要嘅嘅嘅作為stakeholder嘅，啊，咁希望你哋能夠咧，即係充分聽到佢哋聲音啊。
嘅誒過程裏邊咧，誒保險業界一定係有足夠嘅資源或者係誒時間咧，係去誒作出誒佢哋誒對於依個議題。
嘅方法嘅啊，因為如果係呢個將來呢個建議嘅折扣率咧，如果唔能夠同嗰個客觀個經濟數據嘅變動一致咧，噉樣個申索人得到嘅賠款咧，將會現實係脱節嘅啊，噉啊嚴重係失衡。
多謝。多謝，主席。我有個問題，就係關於《P.R.R. Code》付款諮詢，特別係有關問題三，第二節，你講到有關情況，係會唔會公平，由法院下令。
就係關於係誒喺另外一個罪行其中一個例子咧，即係話男女依家嗰個嘅誒，即係所謂嗰個光壓性別唔同嗰度咧。我印象之中咧，其實應該喺我哋之前嘅consultation paper嗰度咧，應該都有係去誒掂到嗰樣嘢。嗰個當然嗰個整體嗰個方向咧，其實係誒即係。
應該有嗰個分別嘅，但係我諗我就唔可以好具體答到關於嗰一條嗰度咧。我因為我印象我都唔好去揾翻以前嗰份報告咧，去睇翻。咁可唔可以承諾即係整體，無論你今次或者你話之前已經處理過、提出過有關性別唔同而嗰個年齡唔同或者個刑罰唔同嘅，你最後？
都係會等齊而唔會出邊出現差異咧。誒，我諗咁講咧，就誒，我自己睇翻咧，我哋個權限咧，我哋就做唔到任何承諾嘅，因為我哋係一個嘅消組委員會咧，好多都喺法律會嗰度去做。咁但係我諗整體方向咧，我哋應該好清楚咧，喺幾份嘅諮詢文件裏面咧，我哋都講咗我。
係好誒咁誒，可能有補充，係嘅，係嘅。關於誒剛才啊啊張立明教授亦都提到，就係話，即係其實成個小組委員會本身佢喺討論誒有任何建議嘅時候咧，都有啲大原則係跟進，包括話唔會因為性傾向咧係作出歧視。咁至於再具體細節話。
話會個別嘅項目入邊會係點樣？因為其實誒，正如一開始我哋嘅小組委員會主席都指出，就話我哋係將報告書個建議書嘅頭嗰三部分咧，會統合咁整嚟嘅，包括話第二部分涉及到小朋友嘅情況啊，等等，即係兒童嘅情況。咁所以喺佢哋檢討有關收入到意見之後咧，會一拼去處理嘅。多謝主。
好誒，跟住落嚟就係陳建波議員。好啊，多謝主席嗱。我會誒就改革按期支付未來金額損失個賠款咧發言嘅。我首先多謝阿貝禮達律師咧，係就講得出我哋保險界嗰個關注，噉我好認同佢佢講嗰啲嘅，特別係有啲誒。
誒，再一般保險嘅係咪應該承擔一啲長期保險嗰種責任咧？將來點做咧噉樣嚇咁？但係我首先講咧，就保險界咧將會係好詳盡咁回應個諮詢文件。但係喺呢個階段咧，我想指出兩點啊。第一咧就係話呢個改革咧係會影響個法定強制性保險嘅險種嘅，例如係僱員保險啦、汽車保險啦、船舶。
選誒保險啦，同埋呢個法律責任嘅保險嘅咁涉及咧幾十萬嘅投保人，當中有僱主啦、車主啦、駕駛人啦、船主同埋營運商、大廈業主、立法團等等呢一類嘅保險加埋嘅總保費咧，而家係每年超過一百億嘅。咁所以有關嘅改動可能令到個賠款增加。如果賠償增加五個percent咧，我。
我哋嘅保費，香港嘅保費就會增加五億噉，所以對呢啲保單持有人嚟講咧，嗰個賠償開支引起嘅保費嘅增幅咧，肯定就係佢哋考慮嘅關鍵。所以除咗呢個公眾諮詢之外咧，喺落實政策之前咧，我哋覺得咧係應該要進行獨立嘅、詳細嘅、深入嘅研究，去評估呢一個改革會為呢個整體。
社會帶嚟嘅成本效益啦，同埋佢嗰個誒，佢個成本同效益係咪成正比例咧？而且係應該有同嗰啲持份者溝通啊，包括車主啦、僱主啦、保險保險業監理局啦、保險聯會等等。另外，保險業界亦都好建，亦都係建議局方咧，考慮係咪需要徹底改革計算折扣率。
所以咧，法改會咧應該值得咧，係同時就兩者咧進行獨立嘅研究嚇。喺完成折扣率嘅研究之後咧，先決定咧用咩方法咧去呢個誒進行啦。例如係咪需要授權某啲機構咧去檢討同埋定定咧相關嘅折扣率嘅？噉我知道咧，誒你哋都會喺七月三號同保險業聯
and in fact.
啊，periodical payment。
啊！多謝大家先，有冇任何嘅補充？Any additional comments you want to make on the on both matters?
But I'm I'm interested in knowing what sort of factors would the court normally take into account to decide this question, and how you can help people to understand the consultation, especially this question, a little bit better.
In fact, if one follows the model of other overseas jurisdiction, the circumstances under which the court will review the terms of a periodic payment order is in fact very limited.
好誒，據我理解，依個一個意見嚟嘅嚇。誒，想邊一位回應咧？係啊，睇下有冇邊位回應？有冇邊位會回應啊？陳傑波議員嘅意見？Any？誒，其實誒，陳傑波議員頭先提嗰兩點咧，其實我哋都有聽聞嘅。咁如果陳傑波議員睇下嗰個誒諮詢文件第。
誒六點七零嗰段咧都有記載啊！依兩點咁當然我哋喺制定依個誒諮詢文件嘅時候咧，誒係亦都有誒領會到誒保險業界嘅誒朋友或者一啲同事嘅擔心。當然喺依個諮詢。
嘅一啲嘅意見啦。咁當然就係七月三號會一個誒會面，咁希望大家喺交流嘅情況底下可以就互相瞭解多一些。係啦，我哋嘅目的都係想一方面能夠平衡嗰個誒申索人嗰個嘅錢能夠運用得更好啦，或者個賠償更加配合佢需要嘅。但係另一方面咧，都一定會有個社會代價啦。
It has to be the circumstances which is anticipated upon expert advice at the time the order is made. In the event that there is anticipated major deterioration on the condition of the recipient of periodic payment, or in the
event of substantial improvement of the condition of the recipient, then there will be very detailed criteria set out at the time the order is made for either party to come back to court to seek a variation of the order.
And there will also be a limitation on the number of application that can be made, and therefore it is not an open-ended commitment. And that is basically a question that is geared towards this type of situation, so as to do justice to both parties.
The adjustment on the basis of substantial improvement of the recipient is something that is new. That would not be the same as the current regime of provisional damages as allowed by the rules of High Court as it now stands. Yes, thank you for that clarification.
嗯。
討論，Further discussion， and thank you all for coming today for such long meeting, for for all these issues that has drawn a lot of concern from our panel. But your opinions have been very very valuable for us. Thank you very much. Thank you.
I think this is set out also in the body of the consultation paper. Indeed, yeah. And also in terms of timetable, what are you looking at? I mean, this consultation will go on, and when do you expect to produce a report, so that we could help you push the government to, you know, do to do to adopt.
Stop your recommendations and take this forward. Well, I don't think I can say anything to bind my colleagues and also those assisting us. Of course, to a large extent, it depends on the number and volume of the submission that we received upon expiry of the.
consultation period on the 24th of August, but in a rough and ready approach, I personally would be aiming at producing a final report within about a year, and it is contemplated that if the result of the consultation is such that we feel that
We are in a position to make more definitive recommendation. We will perhaps attempt a draft of the legislation that is needed to bring about the reform, so as to expedite matters. 好，首先咧就。
O.K.如果冇咧，就係噉樣啊。剛才陳志全議員話，即係都希望我哋啊委員會探討下會唔會有一個公聽會咧，我就會噉樣處理嘅。我會同啊秘書處同埋咧，我都徵詢下其他嘅委員啊嘅意見嚇。噉我自己個人呢個問題咧，都係比較。
開放嘅態度，但係由於咧，我哋嗰啲時間表而家去到七月係排得好緊嘅嗱。萬一喺誒時間上安排唔到咧，我都希望誒誒法改委嗰邊啦，亦都聽到我哋意見，就係話萬一我哋係誒誒，亦都有啲意見係遲咗嘅，你哋係可以都誒盡量。
聆聽，我頭先即係就咁輕輕聽到委員嘅問題咧，其實我都覺得佢哋提出嘅問題係好值得你哋去參考。可能我哋其實需要多少少時間嘅。噉我我諗你哋可以誒，我哋會通知翻你哋，我哋會唔會誒能夠及時舉行到個聽證會咧？如果唔得嘅話，
就希望你哋喺時間上咧，就都通融一下咧。誒，我哋如果又仲有個別嘅委員有意見咧，你哋係可以即係聆聽同埋考慮埋嘅，好冇啊嚇。Okay，so um that is how I would handle the request of the public hearing on the matter， and I I think the matter is very worthwhile for